<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Rome's rarities, or, The Pope's cabinet unlock'd and exposed to view ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 218KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 101 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B29063</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11634207</idno>
  <idno type="VID">199119</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240870582</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1904</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11634207</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B29063)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199119)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 3:46e)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Rome's rarities, or, The Pope's cabinet unlock'd and exposed to view ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 191 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for James Norris,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: mutilated; imprint lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199119:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ROMES</hi> RARITIES; OR THE <hi>Pope's Cabinet</hi> UNLOCK'D, And Expos'd to View.</p>
            <p>BEING A true and Faithful Account of the Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphemy, Treason, Massacres, Murders, Lechery, Whoredom, Buggery, Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Debauchery, Pious Frauds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Romish Church, from the Pope himself to the Priest, or inferiour Clergy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:199119:2"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> he had Judgment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Historical Relation of several Great and Learned <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manists</hi> who did Imbrace the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> with their Reasons for their Change, deliver'd in their own words. 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Seasonable Collection of plain Text of Scripture, for the Use of <hi>English Protestants.</hi> price 2 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:199119:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Triple-Crown'd Prelate OF ROME.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>HOLY SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Do here, with all imaginable Deference and Humility, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent you (I will not be so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly as to say, with <hi>a Pig of your own Sow,</hi> but) with a Rich Cabinet, and good reason too, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause your own: for 'tis unjust that you should be the Proprietor, and another the Usufrctuary. A
<pb facs="tcp:199119:3"/>Cabinet, wherein are display'd all the commendable Qualifications, and inimitable Perfections of some of your Famous Predecessors, that have had the Honour to sit in S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s Chair; and in some particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, a weak Character or Adum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of your Holiness's Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which no Pen can fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineate. Nor can you any way complain of foul play herein, since this Tract contains no Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations but what are collected from the most Authentic and rigid <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manists</hi> that ever espoused the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Cause and Persuasion.</p>
            <p>The Candid Reader, by a seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perusal of this Treatise, will, I presume, not onely receive sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction thereby, but also make a Discovery of those rare Vertues
<pb facs="tcp:199119:3"/>which embellish the minds of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Successors, more to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown and Glory, than the resplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Diamonds and Rubies that shine in, and adorn the Triple Diadem; and therefore, I hope, that your Sanctity will leave the Author out when you presume to Curse all Hereticks (as you miscall them) once a Year in the <hi>Bulla Coenae;</hi> or otherwise you shall hear of him agen in a more Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>castic Style and Satyrick Humour, this being only at present Joco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serious. If any thing herein clinch too close, and offend; let those of your own Party beg your pardon, (whose Duty it is) that afforded the Materials, which, compiled together and collected, make up this Epitome of your Memorable
<pb facs="tcp:199119:4"/>Acts and Monumental Transacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But withall, I must needs confess, that no Bigoted Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant, who moves in the highest Sphere of Ecclesiastical Dignity, dares presume or pretend to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to the height of those Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies herein mentioned, which are only peculiar to the <hi>Roman</hi> Miter. If the subordinate Clergy storm at the Contents of this Book, let them thank themselves for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing to the Public their Cheats and Chicaneries so apparently, that an inconsiderable Lay-Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant could not possibly avoid ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king notice of, he being only the <hi>Amanuensis</hi> of their own Authors, and hath taken the pains to trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe out of them such Memorials as he thought convenient to reduce
<pb facs="tcp:199119:4"/>to the Method observ'd in this small System or Collection. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath this <hi>Aurea Legenda</hi> to your Holiness first, and then to the rest of the Inferiour Clergy; it being a Brat of their own Brain, a Babe of their own Procreation; and so bid you all farewel, who sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe my self</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Philanax Misopapas.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:199119:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199119:5"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Pope's Cabinet</hi> UNLOCK'D.</head>
            <p>A <hi>Papa Principium.</hi> Why not this as good an Invocation now-a-days, as <hi>à Jove Principium,</hi> in times of Yore? for my part, I know no reason to the contrary; since the former is styled God by some, and Vice-God by most <hi>Romanists;</hi> the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter known by all to be no God at all, or at best, a false one. Therefore to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with Holiness must needs be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, nay, with <hi>His Holiness,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that cannot prove successless. Avaunt then, fond Protestant, and do not hit him so often in the teeth with the flurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nick-name of <hi>the Man of Sin.</hi> No,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199119:6"/>no, he's the <hi>Man of Sanctity;</hi> there's the Mistake; nor with that frequent unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly Title of the <hi>Whore of Babylon;</hi> for that is both incoherent with Sense, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>consistent with the Sex; but be not too bold with that Argument, whatever you do, good Papist, for fear some blunt Protestant round you in the Ear (and that he is like enuf to do) with the Story of Pope <hi>Joan,</hi> and tell you to your face, when you say you are abus'd here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that it is with a matter of truth, and shew you good reason for it too; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there be either Truth or reason in a great many of your own Popish Writers, who allow the History to be authentick: but of that more anon. An ordinary Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sician, by the Indisposition of the Head, can soon judge of the Temper of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; and no doubt when the Reader un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstands how this Head of the Church stands affected, he will soon guess at the foulness of the Stomach, and give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the weak and crazy Constituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole Body Ecclesiastick. Do but observe the numerous and haughty
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:199119:6"/>Titles that he so magisterially assumes to himself, as the Universal, the Infallible Bishop of <hi>Rome;</hi> the Head of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, the Supreme Pastor, the Holy one, the Pope, Christ's Vicegerent, God's Vicar, a Vice-god, nay, a God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, and God knows how many more; and then tell me truly, whether in his Pride and number of Names he may not out-vye both <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Persian</hi> (and at length prove as little a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an as either of them) who upon the bare Report of this usurped Authority, have bestow'd on him two glorious Denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, the one calling him <hi>Rumbeg,</hi> that is, Prince or Lord of <hi>Rome,</hi> the other <hi>Rumschah,</hi> King of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First then to begin with the Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies used by several Popes themselves, which are so great, that if Profaneness it self, could it assume an humane Shape, would not be guilty of; and <hi>Lucian,</hi> that Arch-Apostate, were he now alive, would, if compar'd to them, be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moderate.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:199119:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth, Son to the Duke of <hi>Florence,</hi> was a chuck-farthing-Boy Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, who was thought to deserve the Red Hat at the Age of Thirteen, and a Pope at Twenty, the unerring Bishop of <hi>Christendom</hi> in hanging Sleeves, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he could write Man, or of Age, was Father of all the Aged; and truly he verified the old Proverb, <hi>Soon ripe, soon rotten;</hi> for what a more putrid and blasphemous Expression could be belch'd forth by the Devil himself, than that of his, who when Cardinal <hi>Bembo</hi> quoted a place out of the New Testament, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, <hi>Quantum nobis profuit haec Fabul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de Christo,</hi> What Wealth have we gain'd by this Fable of Christ? Was not this becoming Christ's Vicegerent? And after a Dispute <hi>de Anima,</hi> 'twas as good a Sentence of the Good Soul,
<q>Et redit in nihilum quod fuit ante nihil.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Julius</hi> the Third, a mere Epicure, when he was at Table with several Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees of <hi>Rome,</hi> had a Peacock serv'd in at
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199119:7"/>Dinner, (his beloved Dish) and gave strict order it should be kept cold for his Supper; but it seems some of his Servants through neglect dispos'd of it otherwise: now when the time of his Evening Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>past came, and he found it wanting, he fell into so great a Chafe and Rage, for this Sin of Omission in his Servitor, that his Holiness was guilty of a Sin of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission; insomuch, that a more mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Cardinal, one of his Guests, told him, that it was ill done to be so passio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and fly out into so great a Fury for so small a Trifle; but he suddenly replied, If God was so angry as to expel <hi>Adam</hi> Paradise for an Apple, well might he, who was his Vicar, be offended for the Disappointment of his Peacock which was of greater value than any Apple could possibly be.</p>
            <p>The same worthy Pope missing his Pork, which was one of his standing Dishes, (for he was a great Lover of Pork and Peacock) asked the Reason of it; his Steward answer'd, that his Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians had given order there should be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:199119:8"/>no Pork serv'd in because it was very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious and destructive to his Health; whereat he began to fly in the very face of him whose Vicar he boasts himself to be, saying, <hi>Porta mi quello mio Piatto al dispet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to de Dio,</hi> Fetch me my Pork (my Dish of Meat) in spight of God himself. These Words savour of more than <hi>Lucianisme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> the Third, in a Procession at <hi>Rome,</hi> where the Body of Christ, as they term it, was with great Solemnity and seeming Piety carried before him, said, That if the Company did not make more haste he would renounce Christ; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon some Persons made up to them that were in the Front, with all speed, and caused them to mend their Pace. Nay farther,</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Paul</hi> being in an open Consisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Cardinals, boldly told by one of them, that he could not bestow <hi>Palma</hi> and <hi>Piacenza</hi> on his two Bastards, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less he would inevitably purchase his own Damnation. To this he answer'd, If St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the Apostle of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> had so tender an Affection for his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199119:8"/>whom he calls Brethren, as to wish and desire himself to be separate from Christ, so that they might obtain Salvation; why may not I with as great Love and Affection to my Sons and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews, study by all means possible to ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grandize them, and make them honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable with the hazard of my own Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? O the yearning Bowels and tender Compassion of this Holy Father to the living Monuments of his Infamy! Poor cow-hearted <hi>Hugonot!</hi> Where is there a <hi>Calvin, Beza,</hi> or Bishop among you all that dares or can show such strange and strong efforts of a noble and undaunted Spirit, who for the Promotion and Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of his Children here, dares damn his own Soul for ever hereafter? Alas! There's no such Spirit among you.</p>
            <p>What think you of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seventh? tho his proper name (which Popes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce at their Election) was <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> which signifies <hi>Fire-brand of Hell</hi> in the <hi>Tutonick</hi> Tongue, as the <hi>Germans</hi> affirm; and <hi>Chemnitius</hi> gives him the same Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, calling him <hi>Titio Infernalis;</hi> when
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199119:9"/>he consulted the Oracle of his Breaden God, threw it into the Fire, before ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Cardinals, who could not withhold him, because it gave him no answer as to the event of his War with the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth of <hi>France.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Benno Card. in the life of Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debrand.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> Bishop of <hi>Port,</hi> in a Sermon in S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> Church before a numerous Auditory, being upon the profanation of the Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Sacrament, said, <hi>Hildebrand</hi> and we with him have done a Fact for which we Deserve to be Burnt alive; meaning the forementioned Action. Nay, this <hi>Hostia</hi> was so Contemned and Slighted by him, that he most wickedly caused Pope <hi>Victor</hi> the Second to be poisoned with the Consecrated Wine of the Holy Eucharist; and yet Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> had the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to Justifie this Man, as a Saint, by Twenty seven Authors; and another had the impudence to own him as a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniz'd Saint by two more, which he throws into the Bargain to add to the former Number; These are a pack of Saints of the Devils Canonizing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:199119:9"/>
            <p> What will you say of another of these Pious Arch Prelates, who was the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that caused the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, surnam'd of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> to be poisoned, and that with the conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated Bread, given him by a Jacobine at <hi>Florence</hi> in the Eucarist.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math. Paris. P.</hi> 88.</note> And about the year 1154 his Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake the Arch Bishop of <hi>York</hi> was poison'd in <hi>England</hi> with the Wine in the Sacrament. What will the Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar's Devil do, trow we, if their God be so dangerous, saith the learned <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Stevens,</hi> who composed this <hi>Huic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> upon the very Subject;
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Les Payens ne vouloyent mettre au nombre des Dieux</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ceux qui au genre humain ètoyent perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieux:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sile Dieu de Paste estun Dieu qui empoisonne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dont l' Empereur Henri tesmoignage nous donne;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Que dicoyent les Payens de ces gentils Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteurs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qui les hommes ont fait de luy Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teurs.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:199119:10"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Car si leur Dieu ne fait de meurtrir conscience,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Entre leur Diable et Dieu quelle est la difference.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ith' number of their Gods <hi>Pagans</hi> we find</l>
                  <l>Ner'e rank't such as were hurtful to Mankind;</l>
                  <l>If that the God of Paste can poison men,</l>
                  <l>As the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> testifies, what then</l>
                  <l>Would <hi>Heathens</hi> of these brave Doctors have said,</l>
                  <l>Who teach Men to adore a piece of Bread?</l>
                  <l>For if their God with Murder can dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence,</l>
                  <l>'Twixt God and Devil what's the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</l>
               </q> As for <hi>Boniface</hi> the Eighth, it is too no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious how he undervalued and vilifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the same Host when he was Prisoner to the <hi>Gibellines</hi> of the Emperour's Faction in the City of <hi>Agnania.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Platina.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Julius</hi> the Second, when he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated by the Earl of <hi>Faix,</hi> and totally routed near <hi>Ravenna,</hi> he out of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Zeal and Fervor (I
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199119:10"/>must not call it Madness, or Irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence) threw away the <hi>Hostia,</hi> and made it be trampled upon by the unsanctified Feet of the rude Multitude, which hath been formerly taken by them with so much Reverence and Adoration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregory</hi> the Ninth renounced the Gospel,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baleus li.</hi> 5. <hi>of the lives of the Popes.</hi>
               </note> and embraced in lieu of it an infamous Legend, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd by as infamous a Monk, <hi>Cyril</hi> by name. Thus you see how these Holy Pastors of Christ's Sheep behave themselves in Person, and this is not all, but their Canons published in Print, and allowed, are as blasphemous as their own common Discourse, or that of their Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sites (who are so far from punishment that they are loaded with Rewards) as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serting the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> to be a God.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dist.</hi> 96. <hi>c. sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis evidenter &amp; Panorm. c. Quanto Abbas.</hi>
               </note> I'll warrant you this bold assertion will frighten the Poor spirited Protestant to his Litany, From such Blasphemy good Lord deliver us.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> is so bold as to couple abomination with the merit of the Holy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199119:11"/>Passion.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap. inter opera Charitatis des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons. l.</hi> 4. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretal.</hi>
               </note> We ordain (saith the Pope) that for all such men who shall take common Strumpets out of the Stewes and Marry them; that it shall advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage them as to the remission of Sin.</p>
            <p>Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Pope over the Church Militant <hi>etiam Christo secluso;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bell. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Pontif. c.</hi> 9.</note> Christ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing secluded from him.</p>
            <p>His Flatterers exclude all Patriarchs and Bishops, from the Popes Lieutenancy to the Son of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>C. quanto l.</hi> 1. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretal. tit.</hi> 7. <hi>de translat. Episcop.</hi>
               </note> in these words. That he executeth not the Function of a meer Man here upon Earth, but of a true God. Nay farther;
<note place="margin">V. Gl. v. Veri Dei. cap. unico. De jurejurando. gl. v. Vicarium in Clement.</note> That the Pope is able to change the nature of things: That his Authority is heavenly; that of nothing he can make something, (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the old Rule <hi>ex nihilo nihil fit</hi>) that his Will is sufficient for Reason; that none may be so bold as to question him; that he can dispence above the Law, that he can make Justice of Injustice,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:199119:11"/>that he hath fulness of Power; And else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can. omnes Dist.</hi> 22. <hi>cap. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> that every Creature is subject to him, that he hath the Rights of Heavenly and Earthly Empire.</p>
            <p>Nay they proceed in higher strains, and say, We declare and define,
<note place="margin">Extrav. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mun. c. Ʋnam sanctam de Majorit. &amp; obedien. See all the gloss of the chapt.</note> that it is necessary to Salvation for all Creatures, in all things, and in all places to be under the Bishop of <hi>Rome.</hi> Observe what the Blasphemous <hi>Parasite</hi> saith, Our Lord would have been very indiscreet,
<note place="margin">Bertrand. in gl. Extrav. com. cap. u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam sanctam de majorit. Petri.</note> if he had not left a Man behind him, that had an equal power with himself. To conclude this sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, take an abstract of this Oration pronounced in the <hi>Lateran</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, printed by the Authority of <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth, in the presence of the whole Council.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orat. Ant. Puccii Clerici. Apostol.</hi> 3. <hi>Non. Maiae</hi> 15, 15 <hi>sess.</hi> 10.</note> Although the Aspect of your Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty by whose resplendent glory my weak Eyes are dazzled. Again, In thee alone, the true
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:199119:12"/>and Lawful Vicar of Christ and God, this Prophecy is to be fulfilled, All the Kings of the Earth shall worship him, and all Nations serve him, <hi>Psalm</hi> 71. Then, he saith; Before, and now the Universal Body of the Church is subject to one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Head, <hi>viz.</hi> unto Thee. <hi>Item,</hi> Knowing that to thee alone hath been given all Power from the Lord in Heaven and Earth, that thou mayest judge, not only Spiritual, but also the Earthly Powers of the World. If this be not like the Man of Sin, to exalt himself above God, let all men judge.</p>
            <p>Another Flatterer was General of the Order of Preachers, who received a Cardinal's Cap as the Guerdon of his Blasphemies;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sess.</hi> 2. <hi>in orat. Cajetam.</hi>
               </note> It shall obtain, if you will (speaking of the Church) and command it, if you imitate the Power and Perfection of the Almighty, whose Lieutenant you are here upon Earth; not only in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Dignity, but affection of Will. Gird your Swords (for you have two, the Spiritual and Temporal) one common to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:199119:12"/>other Princes, the other belongs to you only: And speaking of the Pope's Mercy; It will render you worthy of Worship, Gracious and most like unto God. And afterwards, by the Mercy of God &amp; yours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and so runs on with such a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Series of Blasphemies, as Black as the Hat could be Red, which he purchased by his Adulation in this Hyperbolical Elogy of his Imperious Master.</p>
            <p>But I presume I have tortur'd you suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently with this horrid Discourse; therefore I close it with the Words of <hi>Seneca;</hi>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Magne Regnator Deum, tam lentus audis scelera!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tam lentus vides; Ec quando saeva fulmen emittes manis?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Great God of Heaven! can'st thou both hear and see</l>
                     <l>Such horrid Crimes as these so patiently?</l>
                     <l>When will thy incens'd Justice send, I wonder,</l>
                     <l>From thy Almighty hand revenging Thunder.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:199119:13"/>
            <p> The next Vertues that qualifie them for the Papal Chair, are Chastity, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinencie and Abstinence from Carnal Lusts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and how well they are gift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with these will appear by the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Examples.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>John</hi> the Thirteenth was a Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of Men, nay, of Popes too; who, as it was articled against him in a General Council, committed Incest with two of his Sisters, deflowred innocent Virgins, lay with <hi>Stephana</hi> his Fathers Concubine (a lovely Generation, like Father like Son) with <hi>Raynera</hi> a Widow, and one <hi>Anna,</hi> with her Neece likewise. He was a great Enemy to the Married Clergy; and from him <hi>Dunstan</hi> received a Commission to be unnaturally incestuous.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Sylvius</hi> left a brace of Bastards here in <hi>England,</hi> the one got on a Scotch, and the other on an English Woman; nay, whilst he was Cardinal, he kept his Concubine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> the Twelvth was kill'd by the Devil in the Act with another man's Wife, saith <hi>Sigebert;</hi> but others report that he was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the Act, and by the hand of an abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:199119:13"/>Husband, like <hi>Zimri,</hi> had the just re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of his foul and open Adultery; for the fatal gash that he receiv'd sent him pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the other World in Eight days time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rodorique Borgia,</hi> stiled <hi>Alexander</hi> the Sixth after he came to the Papacy, was the first Pope that was so ingeniously modest as to own his Bastards,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Guicciard. Hist. Ital.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 10.</note> and tho his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors disguised them under the appellation of Nephews and God-sons, (looking upon Fig-leaves to be some, tho but a slender covering of Nakedness,) yet he was so shameless in his Lust, as publikly to acknowledge his base Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spring; and particularly took cognizance of <hi>Caesar Borgia,</hi> one that had a Soul of as swarthy a Complexion as his Father, and procur'd him a red Hat; but he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing soon weary of the Gospel, which might well be asham'd of him, did as sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly procure a Dispensation to un-Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal himself; these two committed In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cest with their own Sister,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Guicciardin. l.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 179.</note>
               <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eretia</hi> by name; as famous for Whoredom in the new, as her
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:199119:14"/>Name-sake for Chastity in old <hi>Rome;</hi> of whom <hi>Pontanus</hi> writes this Epitaph.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Conditur hoc tumulo Lucretia nomine, sed re Thais, Pontificis Filia, Sponsa, Nurus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Here lies <hi>Lucrece</hi> by Name, <hi>Thais</hi> in Life,</l>
                  <l>The Pope's Child, Spouse, and yet his own Son's Wife.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>He caused his eldest Brother, the Duke of <hi>Candia,</hi> to be murthered as he rode one Night in the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> and his Body cast into <hi>Tyber,</hi> because he thought him a Rub in his way to Preferment. He was, like his Father, very lavish in his Lust, insomuch that he did not forbear to tread both Hen and Chicken when the Fit was upon him; nay, at the taking of <hi>Capua,</hi> where he assisted the <hi>French,</hi> he had a Reserve of no less than forty of the fairest Ladies for his own use, to satiate his inordinate Lust.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Martin</hi> the 4th kept his Predecessor's Harlot, (<hi>Nicholas</hi> 3.) and was so tender of her, that he caused all deformed Pictures to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:199119:14"/>be remov'd out of his Palace, for fear she should be delivered of a monstrous ugly Child. Surely if his Holiness was so kind to a Whore he would be very fond of a Wife.</p>
            <p>Of this Pope's Simony, which he was compelled to for the maintaining his own and his Nephew's Incests and lustful Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies, there is extant this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stich:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vendit Alexander Claves, Altaria, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vendere jure potest, emerat ille prius.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> sells Christ, Altars, Keys,</l>
                  <l>And well he might; for first he bought all these.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Alexander</hi> the Sixth dispenced with <hi>Peter Mendoza,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Valencia,</hi> to use his Bastard Son, the Marquess of <hi>Zannet,</hi> as his Ganymede or Sodomitical Boy: insomuch that <hi>Charles</hi> the Eighth being at <hi>Rome,</hi> during his Pontificate, he was so hated by, and odious to all Men, that the whole Conclave of Cardinals (two only excepted) did entreat him to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:199119:15"/>vindicate the Holy Church from the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence and Tyranny of the Pope, who was rather a Successor of <hi>Judas</hi> than St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and a greater Observer of the Alcoran than the Gospel. A fine Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a Pope from his own Cardinals!</p>
            <p>A <hi>German</hi> Prince sent an Ambassador to the Pope, who after he was dispatch'd, taking his leave of his Holiness, he in Latin said to him, Tell our beloved Son, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which put the honest <hi>German</hi> into such a Chafe, that he had almost affront<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Pope with the Lye; withal rounding him in the Ear, that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster was no Son of a Priest (meaning no Bastard.) See the Chastity of these Holy ones when their Incontinency and Lasci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viousness is grown proverbial.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joan,</hi> Queen of <hi>Naples,</hi> hang'd her first Husband, and before he was cold married the Prince of <hi>Tarentum,</hi> one of the handsomest Men in the Universe; she kept her self in a whole Skin by the Schism that then hapned between Pope <hi>Ʋrban</hi> and <hi>Clement,</hi> and so escaped un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punished, (tho at last she was executed)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:199119:15"/>who bestow'd <hi>Avignon</hi> in <hi>France</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Pope <hi>Ʋrban</hi> and his Successors, under pretence of Sale. This is only to let you know that his Holiness has not so sickly and squeamish a Conscience but he can dispense with a fair, large Gift from a foul, filthy hand: which contributes much to the Justification of the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chastity of <hi>Rome,</hi> since she hath been so great a Gainer by Strumpets and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, Stews and Brothels, a Tribute far worse and baser than that of <hi>Vespasian, ex lotio:</hi> therefore well might honest <hi>Mantuan</hi> say,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I pudor in villas, tota est jam Roma Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panar.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>At wanton <hi>Rome</hi> there is no room we know</l>
                  <l>For Shame-fac'dness, to Hamlets let her go.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Naso,</hi> once a <hi>Roman,</hi> to the shame of such Popes, could sing,
<q>
                  <hi>Turpe Tori reditu census augere paternos.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:199119:16"/>
            <p> What a miserable thing is it that St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> should be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by those who live by the Sweat of their Bodies. In the time of <hi>Paul</hi> the Third, he had upon his Roll or Register 45000 Courtisans (nay, <hi>Naples</hi> the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuous has 20000 registred in the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of <hi>Savelli,</hi> allow'd of.) This Word Courtisan came originally from the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> (the modestest Synonomon of a Whore) <hi>viz.</hi> from those <hi>Religiosa</hi>'s or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Dames who conversed with his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness both at Bed and Board.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Thirteenth was a Man of the same Constitution as the rest of that sanctified Tribe, and was subject to Failings as well as Persons of an infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour degree; witness his Bastard, <hi>James Buoncourpagno,</hi> a good Catholick no doubt, and according to the Proverb, he was very fortunate; for his Holy Father in a double Sense, both Natural and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, gave him <hi>Ireland,</hi> and created him Marquess of <hi>Lemster,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thuan. Hist. l.</hi> 64.</note> Earl of <hi>Wexford,</hi> &amp;c. and sent one <hi>Stukely</hi> to reduce it to his Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:199119:16"/>
            <p> Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Third, encouraged by the Example of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Sixth, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Incest with <hi>Constantia</hi> his own Daughter; but finding that he could not enjoy her as formerly, being married to the Duke of <hi>Sforza,</hi> he poison'd her; and then courted his Sister, and grew ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fond; but he soon dispatch'd her also the same way, because she was not so much delighted with his Embraces as with others.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Martin</hi> the Fifth dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensed with one to marry his own Sister;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anton. Sum. p.</hi> 3. <hi>tit.</hi> 1. &amp;c. one of their own Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> of whom it was a common Lampoon among the People, nay the very Sing-song of little Children in the Streets of <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Il Papa Martino.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non vale un quatrino.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Martin</hi> the Pope</l>
                  <l>Is not worth a Rope.</l>
               </q> An Argument they stand not much in awe of him.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Rome,</hi> the sacred Seat of his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, the Courtizans are many, who are
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:199119:17"/>tolerated and publickly allow'd, for which they pay a smart and certain An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Tribute; and every common Whore is oblig'd to have her Name registred in the Vice-Gerents Office, an Officer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the <hi>Vicario,</hi> the Pope's Vicar General; so that they enjoy an absolute liberty to be licentious throughout the Year, except at the times called <hi>Vacanze,</hi> or Vacation-time, which happens to be about <hi>Christmas</hi> and <hi>Easter;</hi> for then the <hi>Sbirri,</hi> or Bailiffs, may make a strict Search in all their Houses, and if they find any there, may commit them to Goal; but by paying a Sum of Money, they send to the Office, and so prevent their being molested by such kind of Persons. Nay, in those infamous Houses those Harlots boldly and impudently commit their Crimes by the Pope's Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation and Protection. When <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xander</hi> the Seventh sate in the Pontifical Chair, there was some discourse of sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing these Brothel Houses, but it was but Talk; yet it occasion'd this impious and horrid <hi>Pasquinata, Laudate Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:199119:17"/>Pueri.</hi> This <hi>Rome</hi> is that famous holy City, and the City of his Holiness, but the honest Carmelite <hi>Mantuan</hi> tells you a quite contrary Tale, when he saith,</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vivere qui sancte cupitis, discedite Roma:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Omnia cum liceant, non licet esse bonum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>You that will live well must leave <hi>Rome,</hi> for there</l>
                  <l>All things are lawful but what lawful are.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Or thus.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>You that will pious be, shun <hi>Rome,</hi> for now</l>
                  <l>All things but being good they do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 4th had his Strumpet <hi>Tiresia,</hi> built Stews at <hi>Rome,</hi> which yielded him an annual Income of 2000 Ducats, and gave a Dispensation to all the Family of the Cardinal of St. <hi>Lucie</hi> to commit a Sin not to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med among modest <hi>Hugonots,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vessel. Groving Tract. de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent. citat. à Jac. Laur.</note> during the three hot Months of <hi>June, July,</hi> and <hi>August.</hi> And this made <hi>Pasquin</hi> cry out,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:199119:18"/>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>At</hi> Romae <hi>Puero non licet esse mihi.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A Boy to <hi>Rome</hi> must never come.</l>
               </q> This sin the <hi>Italians</hi> say is (if in any) excusable in them, because they live near his Holiness, who doth not only give Licence by permission, but a President by his own Example; this is a common Adage among them.</p>
            <p>We cannot I think bring up the rear of these Chaste ones with any other Person, fitter or more deserving, than Madam <hi>Gilberta,</hi> commonly called Pope <hi>Joan,</hi> a strapping Lass indeed. She was once a Maid of <hi>Mentz</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> sans doubt, and after Miss to a Monk of <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> with whom she ran away to <hi>Athens</hi> in Man's Apparel, and there did coha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit with him, till he unkindly forsook her, and went into the other World; all which time that she did reside there with him, she personated the Man so lively, and wore the Breeches so well and handsomly, as some Viragoes will do, that she bid defiance to all Discovery of her so cunningly counterfeited Sex. Well, what then? Why having lost her belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:199119:18"/>Gallant she trips away to <hi>Rome,</hi> and had made so great a Progress in all the Liberal Arts and Sciences, that she was thought worthy, it seems, of a Cardinal's Cap, and at last of the Triple Crown, and for two years and a half behav'd her self very notably, and wanted no Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication becoming the Papal Chair, but that of her Sex. Yet see how Murder will come out at last. Going in a so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Procession to the Church of St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Lateran,</hi> between <hi>Colosses</hi> and St. <hi>Clements,</hi> she by the way, in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Street, was rid of her vicious Life and an infamous Burden both together; (a pretty teeming Prolifick Papess, this must needs be a Babe of Grace that her Holiness was delivered of, and she the Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> in a double Sense) and at the very place where this unlucky Accident hapned there was erected the <hi>Colonna infame,</hi> or infamous Pillar, (as they ever after called it) in memory of this Accident, to the end it might the better be transmitted to Posterity; and out of a zealous Abhorrence of so black
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:199119:19"/>a Deed, her Successors baulk that way in their usual Processions, and steer ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther course to this very day. But this is not all; to prevent such Female Gossips for the future from putting the like Tricks upon the Conclave of Cardinals, they prudently found out the Porphyry Chair, an infallible Invention to avoid such gross Mistakes, to the Prejudice of Infallibility, and the Shame and Scandal of the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion. Thus far <hi>Plati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> in his Life of that Papess, who was a great Friend to Popes, wrote the Lives of Popes down to his time, was Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to a Pope, and dedicated his Book to a Pope; and indeed the Story were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most incredible had he not the Suffrage of fifty more of their own Authors to justifie his Writing upon this Subject, tho Card. <hi>Baronius</hi> leaves her out; of whom we may truly say, as <hi>Scaliger</hi> did, <hi>Facit Annales non scribit,</hi> He makes Chronicles, but writes them not.</p>
            <p>But here will arise possibly a Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, How comes it to pass that this Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyry Chair is now laid aside? That's a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:199119:19"/>poignant one, upon my Word: but the Catholicks may be satisfied, if they please, with the Answer of <hi>John Pontanus</hi> in an Epigram of his, translated by Mr. <hi>Stevens</hi> into French, which runs thus:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nul ne pouvoit jouir des saintes Clefs de Rome,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sans monstrer q'uil avoit les marques de vray homme,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>D'ou vient donc a present ceste preuve est cessée</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et qu'on n'a plus besoing de la Chaire persée?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cest pource que ceux la qui ores les Clefs ont,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Par les Enfans qu'ils font monstrent bien ce qu'ils sont.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>None had the Keys of <hi>Rome</hi> in times of yore,</l>
                     <l>But such as shew'd true marks of Man before.</l>
                     <l>How comes it then that this Proof's now laid by,</l>
                     <l>And that the Porphyry stool is useless? Why?</l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:199119:20"/>
                     <l>Because those now, who sit ith Papa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Chair,</l>
                     <l>By the base Brats they get show what they are.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But I blush to think that I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the chaste ears of the Protestant Reader by harping so long upon such loose Notes, and made his Cheeks glow at the rehearsal of such immodest actions, therefore I'll leave off this filthy discourse, and see if I can hit upon a more cleanly Argument, not troubling you with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thilda, Gregory</hi> 7th<hi>'s</hi> Miss, nor with <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> the third's <hi>Morezia,</hi> nor a <hi>Donna Olympia,</hi> fresh in the memory of most men of this Age.</p>
            <p>As for the Popes Humility, Poverty, Patience, Clemency and Blood-guiltiness, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> take these few Examples for instance.</p>
            <p>The Proud and Magisterial name of Universal Bishop, <hi>Rome</hi> was at first a mere Stranger to; and <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, a Learned, Good man, declar'd it to be the name of Antichrist, a name of Blasphemy, and to admit it was to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:199119:20"/>shipwrack the Faith.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Greg. l.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 76.83. <hi>Ep.</hi> 78.</note> See here one Pope Proclaiming ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Antichrist. But bold <hi>Boniface</hi> the third, his Successor, received the Title of Universal Bishop from <hi>Phocas,</hi> who murthered the Emperour <hi>Mauritius</hi> and all his Family, and usurped the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Constantinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The blessed Apostle St. <hi>James,</hi> called by the Antients the Bishop of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, <hi>Clem. Epist.</hi> 1. who was a Prince of the Blood Royal, and Cousin German to our Saviour, was President in the first Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil; though he gave his opinion last, yet he took upon him no Superiority above others, and within the bounds of such Christian modesty did the Holy Prelates of Christendom contain themselves, till the year 607.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Venetians</hi> were Excommunicated by Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the fifth for attempting to besiege <hi>Ferrara,</hi> which is Tributary to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> whereupon <hi>Francis Dandalo,</hi> afterwards Grand <hi>Dogue</hi> of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> went to <hi>France,</hi> where the Pope then had his Seat; submissively to beg his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:199119:21"/>Pardon for that imaginary Offence; when he arriv'd there he spent much time 'ere he could be admitted, but at last he was brought into his presence with an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Iron Chain or Dog's collar about his Neck, crawling on all four the length of the great Hall,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sabellicus in fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> 9 <hi>Aeneid. l.</hi> 7.</note> and afterwards lay among the Dogs under his Table, till his wrath was appeas'd; and then he obtain'd a Pardon, for which Act he was ever after called Dog by his own Countrymen. Surely he very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deservedly had the Name of <hi>Clement,</hi> who could be so inhumane and haughty to an ancient Person, and treat him so currishly, that prostrated himself at his Feet with so much slavish submission.</p>
            <p>This Pope walking through the City <hi>Bogenci</hi> upon the River <hi>Loire</hi> in great State, had for his Attendants or Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, the Kings of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> one upon his right, the other on his left hand, and one leading his Horse by the Bridle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third, after he obtain'd the Popedom, had many dangerous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:199119:21"/>with the Emperour <hi>Frederick Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barossa,</hi> and was so often worsted by him, that he was forced to fly to <hi>Venice,</hi> and there live for some time <hi>incognito,</hi> in the habit of a Cook (a prety greazy Disguise for a Pope; see what necessity will do; who would have thought so proud a Bishop should stoop to so base a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>descention) but at last he was known, and honourably embraced by the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians;</hi> and this coming to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Ear, he was highly offended at them for entertaining his Enemy, inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that he sent his Son with a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Army, and great Navy, to take the Pope by force and violence; but the young Prince had the ill fate in that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to be taken Prisoner by the <hi>Venetians,</hi> nor could his freedom be pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly procur'd, unless <hi>Frederick</hi> would come in his own Person to <hi>Venice,</hi> and endeavour to be reconcil'd to the Pope; which the Emperour, for his Son's sake, condescended to; went to <hi>Venice,</hi> and procur'd it upon these unreasonable and Unchristian conditions. That he should
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:199119:22"/>restore the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> and all the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties thereof, and undergo such further Penance as the Pope should injoyn. This being submitted to, the Emperour came to the Door of St. <hi>Mark</hi>'s Church, the People being Spectators, where the proud Pope commanded him very impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously to ly prostrate on the Ground, and to ask his Pardon and Forgiveness; and then he gently treading upon his Neck, prophanely wrested the 13 verse of the 91 Psalm, to his own purpose, saying; Thou shalt walk upon the Aspe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Basilisk, and shalt tread upon the Lion and Dragon; And when the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour said unto him <hi>Non tibi sed Petro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cujus Successor es, pareo;</hi> the Pope repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Et mihi &amp; Petro,</hi> proudly placing himself before the blessed Apostle, whose immediate Successor he falsly pretends to be. See the unexampled humility of this <hi>Servus Servorum Dei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Platina,</hi> in the Life of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seventh, tells you, that the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth of <hi>France,</hi> commonly stiled the Great, was Excommunicated
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:199119:22"/>by the Pope, and that for a Trifle too. The Emperour being inform'd of this his rigorous proceedings, came to <hi>Canosse</hi> (where his Holiness was then dallying with his wanton <hi>Mathilda</hi>) and divest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himself of his Imperial Robes (fine work indeed that the Scepter must bow to the Crosier) went bare-foot and bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, in the depth of a hard Winter, to the City Gates, and there humbly crav'd Admittance; but his Entry was denied, and he, like an obedient Son of that See, bore it with unimaginable and uncommon Patience, remaining three dayes complete in the Suburbs fasting, continually beging Absolution, which at length by the earnest Intercession, and repeated Request of <hi>Mathilda,</hi> the Popes Minion, or St. <hi>Peters</hi> Daughter as they call'd her, the Earl of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and the Abbot of <hi>Cluniac,</hi> was obtain'd. A brave Jaunt indeed for a Puissant Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate, at such an Unseasonable time of the Year, and very kind usage he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd for his pains, but this must be done or he is undone, and forfeits all his
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:199119:23"/>
               <hi>Regalia,</hi> for disobliging a proud, peevish Pope. Where is there ever a <hi>Gueux</hi> of you all that has so much courage to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain your Protestant Privileges and Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Dignity? But one Swallow makes no Summer; all Frenchmen are not so soft Spirited.</p>
            <p>Well fare <hi>Philip</hi> the Fourth, surnamed <hi>Philip Le Bel,</hi> who in the year 1320 had to do with a Monster of a Man, <hi>Boniface</hi> the eighth, when <hi>France</hi> shook off the Supremacy of the Pope in <hi>Temporalibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Prelate wrote to the King in these and such like arrogant Terms: We will that thou know,
<note place="margin">Annales Nic: Giles.</note> thou art our Subject in Spirituals, as well as Temporals. To which the King return'd this Princely answer,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sciat fatuitas ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stra,</hi> &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ta tresgrande sottise scache</hi> &amp;c. Let your Sottishness and gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Temerity know, that in Temporals w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have none but God for Superior <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And not being satisfied with this, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> commanded a Lord of <hi>Languedoc,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Albigeois,</hi> of the House of <hi>Nogaret,</hi> to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:199119:23"/>Seize on the Pope, which he did, and withal gave him such a Blow on the Ear with a Gantlet that fell'd him, for saying his Father was Burnt for an Heretick, and afterwards cast him into Prison, where he died of a Phrenzie, gnawing his own hands out of Rage and Fury, and left this worthy <hi>Elogium</hi> or Epitaph behind him. <hi>Intravit ut Vulpes, regnavit ut Leo, mortuus est ut Canis.</hi> He entred the Papacy like a Fox,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jo. Andr. &amp; Bald. c.</hi> 1. <hi>defend. gl. ad</hi> 6. <hi>Decretal.</hi>
               </note> reigned like a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and died like a Dog. Twas valiantly done of the Stout <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur</hi> to knock down four at a Blow, the <hi>Campanian,</hi> the Cardinal, <hi>Boniface</hi> the Eighth and the Pope; This Pope was so shameless as to boast (having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied three times to confer the Title of Emperour of <hi>Germany</hi> upon the Duke of <hi>Austria</hi>) that he himself was Lord and Emperour of the whole World. Nor did <hi>Lewis</hi> the Twelfth stand in awe of the Pope, whose <hi>Motto</hi> was, <hi>Perdam Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonis nomen,</hi> I will destroy the name of <hi>Babylon.</hi> But this usurped power of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:199119:24"/>the See of <hi>Rome</hi> is but Novel, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern, for instead of their deposing Kings, they deposed Popes; nay <hi>Constantius</hi> the Son of <hi>Constantine</hi> the Great, depos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Pope <hi>Liberius;</hi> the Emperour <hi>Otho</hi> Pope <hi>John</hi> the Twelfth, <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, <hi>Bennet</hi> the Ninth, <hi>Sylvester</hi> the Third and <hi>Gregory</hi> the Sixth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Platina in vit. Greg.</hi> 6. <hi>Abbas Vesp. anno</hi> 1406.</note> and <hi>Sigismund</hi> deposed as many more at one time. The <hi>French</hi> Kings have not only outed but created many Popes formerly. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> the Fair displac'd <hi>Boniface</hi> the Eighth, who translated the See to <hi>Avignon,</hi> where it continued 74 years, and by the King's appointment Six Popes succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one another in that place. And this right of dethroning Popes is treated of by a Chanellor of the <hi>Academy</hi> at <hi>Paris, Gerson</hi> by name, one of the most learned <hi>Sorbonists,</hi> in his Treatise <hi>de Auferibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Papae.</hi> So that you see they were farr from being Lords in Spiritual and Temporal things originally, what ever they pretend to the contrary: and the saying of Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> in his Eighth
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:199119:24"/>Epistle makes it out, that they which are both Kings and Priests under the Gospel, are Members of the Devil. Thus one Pope contradicts another; yet all infallible. Nay two Popes more <hi>Pelagius</hi> and <hi>Gregory,</hi> look'd upon the Title of Universal Bishop as <hi>nomen Blasphemiae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the gravest Sages and greatest Doctors of them all must needs confess, that the Largest and Fattest of the Popes Possessions, are but the Largesse of Kings, and therfore they have little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to carry themselves so Loftily and Exalt themselves above all, which intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable Insolence makes them guilty of the Blackest of Crimes, Ingratitude, if they are unthankful to their first Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; for <hi>Phocas</hi> an adulterous Assassine the Murtherer of his Master <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Emperour,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 607. <hi>An. mundi</hi> 4559.</note> gave them their Name, and <hi>Pepin</hi> their Revenues. But their carriage, now adays is quite contrary to the Discipline of the Apostles, and humble and Submissive Deportment of St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> who writing to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Mauritius</hi> begins in this lowly Stile,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:199119:25"/>I the unworthy Servant of your Piety <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Li.</hi> 2. <hi>Epist.</hi> 61. <hi>in dict.</hi> 11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Nor was <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth terrified by Pope <hi>Paschal</hi> the Second, who wrought upon his own Son to rebell against his Father, (but what may not Infallibility countenance and approve) insomuch that he surprised his Father with great For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, divested him of his <hi>Regalia,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Empire; insomuch that the Aged Potentate died with Grief: and this <hi>Paschal</hi> was so inhumane as to deny him Inhumation, not permitting him to have Christian Burial for five Years after his Death. But <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth, the new Emperour, went immediately after this into <hi>Italy</hi> to the Pope, who expected to be gratified for his pious assisting the Son to murder the Father, and therefore demanded the Right of Investiture; which so incensed the Emperour, that he took him by the Shoulders, and bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly shook his Holiness into a panick Fear; nor was that all, for he was committed close Prisoner, never to enjoy his Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom unless he renounced his unlawful
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:199119:25"/>Claim to Investitures and Collations of Benefices. I could instance in many more; but let these satisfie the Reader, that Princes heretofore did under-value the Pope and his Excommunications, or else the very Citizens of <hi>Rome</hi> would never have presum'd to expell Pope <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the Ninth that City; for indeed they never took any great notice of the Pope's Excommunication. But now to our intended Discourse.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Boniface</hi> the First began first of all to assume the Dominion of the <hi>African</hi> Churches; but he was soon curb'd in his Career by the sixth <hi>African</hi> Council, where the great Pillar of the Western Church was present.
<note place="margin">St. Austin.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, being shrewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly menaced by <hi>Paul</hi> the Third, if he would not surrender <hi>Placentia</hi> to him after the Death of <hi>Peter Lewis;</hi> gave his Holiness to understand, by an Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, that if he would needs be thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d'ring with his Excommunications, he would both thunder and lighten with his Artillery in Answer to him.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:199119:26"/>
            <p> Do but observe the Humility of this Man of God at his Election to the Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. A Fortnights time is appointed for Preparations, in order to the carrying of him with great Pomp and Magnificence, being seated in a Chair of State, is borne on Mens Shoulders to St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Church to possess himself of the Popedom; and if an Emperour happen to be at the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity, it is the greatest Honour he is capable of, to be one of the Bearers of that sanctified Burthen or Lump of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness: and a Fortnight after, or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, he rides in a <hi>Cavalcata</hi> to the Church of St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Lateran</hi> to the same Intent and Purpose.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Platina</hi> tells you in the Life of <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the Fifth, that <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>France, Charles,</hi> the Monsieur, his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and <hi>John</hi> Duke of <hi>Britain,</hi> with many other Persons of the highest Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, were present at his Inauguration, who lost their Lives, many of them being overwhelmed with the fall of a Wall, and buried in the Ruins, King <hi>Philip</hi> being lamed, and his Holiness himself
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:199119:26"/>with an unlucky lucky Blow, was dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted from his <hi>Bucephalus,</hi> and lost a Rubie out of his Miter that cost 6000 Ducats, (how many poor Protestants are worth less that deserve much more) which I do not find by the Relator that it was ever heard of afterwards. Now I leave it to the nice Casuists of their Church, to decide, whether this was not a piece of grand Sacriledge in the Find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to imbezel such Goods as were conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to sacred Uses, and convert them to his own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Frederick</hi> the Emperour waited upon Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> the Fourth, and like an Imperial Groom, quietly held the Stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rop whilst he came off of his Horse; and by all good Signs and Tokens he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a proud taunting Check for his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, in holding the left instead of the right Stirtop; which moved him so much, that he said, I was never brought up to this Trade, and thou art the first upon whom I ever attended so servilely; but for all this he was compell'd, the day following, to hold the right. O brave
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:199119:27"/>Country-man! thou did'st like a bold <hi>Britain,</hi> a true <hi>Nicholas Break-spear</hi> (for that was his Name before his Papificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) that makes no distinction of Persons; and if an Emperour be his Groom he'll make him know his Duty; and Reason good too, if such Potentates will submit to such Servility merely to gratifie the ambitious Humour of a proud Prelate.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Celestine</hi> the Third was to Crown <hi>Hen.</hi> 6th, and his Empress <hi>Constance,</hi> he did it not with his hands but feet; setting it on, and proudly spurning it off again, with these words in his mouth, <hi>Per me Reges regnant.</hi> It is in my sole Power to make and unmake Kings and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</p>
            <p>The State of <hi>Rome</hi> extends three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred miles in length, and two hundred in breadth; and the Pope is able upon occasion to put 50000 men in the Field well equip'd, besides his Naval strength in Gallies, which is very great: Nor is he destitute of Money, for as <hi>Sixtus Quartus</hi> usually said, So long as the Pope can finger a Pen, he can want no
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:199119:27"/>Pence. Besides, the sale of Offices is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gainful; and some reckon that a Pope hath 6000 <hi>l.</hi> a day, besides casual Incomes, which are as advantageous as numerous. The Legate <hi>à Latere,</hi> when he goes abroad upon publick Affairs, hath the allowance of twenty five pound Sterling <hi>per diem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregory</hi> the fifteenth, who sate in the Chair but two years wanting a Month, left his Family 250000 Crowns <hi>per Ann. i.e.</hi> 62500 <hi>l.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the 6th scrap'd up such vast Sums of Money by the sale of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, that his Son <hi>Caesar Borgia</hi> lost one night at Dice 100000 Crowns, saying, <hi>Germanorum tantum haec peccata sunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 5th, of a poor Family, <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retti</hi> by name, tho he was Pope but a lustre of years, erected the Palace <hi>di San Giovanno Laterano,</hi> fortified <hi>Civita Vec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia,</hi> began to build <hi>Monte Cavallo,</hi> foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded many Colleges, and did as many sumptuous and chargeable Works as stood him in fifteen millions of Crowns,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:199119:28"/>that is, four millions of English pounds Sterling, and yet left five millions of Crowns behind him at his decease.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregory</hi> the 15th, who reigned but two years wanting a Month, yet made a poor shift to leave his Family 250000 Crowns a year. If St. <hi>Peter</hi> had been so wealthy, he would not have followed his poor Trade, assure your self; indeed his Successors you see have sailed in his Ship for Traffick with such fortune and success, that they cannot say as he did, without manifest falshood, <hi>Silver and Gold have I none;</hi> for they have scarce any thing else.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> the 5th left 1000 Crowns a day to his Nephew, the Prince of <hi>Salmona,</hi> besides what he bestowed on other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations.</p>
            <p>So much of the Pope's Humility and Lowliness; now for a touch at his Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, Pity, and Mercy.</p>
            <p>And here we must make bold with the Papalines, and beg their pardon, if we prove and reprove the horrid Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of some <hi>Silvesters, Johns, Bonifaces,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:199119:28"/>Julii, Gregories, Sexti</hi> and <hi>Alexanders,</hi> who have either kindled a fire in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Bowels of Christendom, or made her swim in innocent blood.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Hildebrand, Bellarmine</hi>'s Saint, poisoned seven or eight Popes to make way for his obtaining the Papal Chair, and when he enjoy'd it, committed all Barbarisms imaginable, and did hang up men at pleasure, with a <hi>stat pro ratione Voluntas;</hi> My Will is my Law.</p>
            <p>In the Life of <hi>Honorius</hi> the third, it is reported, <hi>Anno</hi> 1223. that one — Bishop of <hi>Cathness</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> was burnt in his Kitchin by the People of his own Diocese, because he excommunicated some of them for Non-payment of Tythes; which Story reaching the Pope's ear, did so distract and discompose his Holiness, that he could not be at rest till he had hang'd four hundred of them, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated all their Children, and all this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufferable Cruelty upon Innocents too, to revenge the Death of one single Person.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Ʋrban</hi> the Fourth instead of <hi>Ʋrbanus</hi> was called <hi>Turbanus,</hi> because he
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:199119:29"/>was so great a Bouteseu, that he set all Christendom in a Combustion.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Ʋrban</hi> the Sixth did, out of a revengeful Spirit, cause five Cardinals to be cast into the River and drown'd.</p>
            <p>It was the usual and pitiful Expression of <hi>Sixtus Quintus,</hi> or <hi>Sise Cinque,</hi> occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd by the Death of a Noble, renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Princess; <hi>Che gusto di tagliar teste cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronate!</hi> Oh what a Pleasure is it to take off crowned Heads! Well said, Reverend Head of the Church! We will take thy bare Word for cutting of Throats with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Security; 'tis honestly done to speak plainly without mental Reservation; for to mince the matter were a piece of Cowardize not to be brook'd in the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Chieftain of the Church Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clement</hi> the Seventh was convicted of notorious Crimes; among the rest, to shew his insatiable Thirst after Blood, he sewed five Cardinals in Sacks (not the five Cardinal Vertues I'll warrant you) and threw them into the Sea; beheaded three more, and after burn'd their Bodies
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:199119:29"/>to Ashes, which he urn'd up in Chests, and placed Cardinals Hats upon them, carrying them about with him where ever he went, to give all People to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand what Reliques were contained in them. And if he were so kind to those of his own Religion, what mercy could others expect from him that were of a contrary Perswasion?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sergius,</hi> who stood Candidate for the Pontificate with <hi>Formosus,</hi> prevail'd so far as to obtain it; and when he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards came to be Bishop of that See, in revenge of his former repulse, compell'd the <hi>Romans,</hi> by his threats and menaces, to make the Ordination of <hi>Formosus</hi> null and void; and made him be taken out of his Grave, (an Act not to be thought on without horror) after he had layn there a considerable time, and then rob'd him with the Papal Vesture, plac'd him in St. <hi>Peters</hi> Chair, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to be beheaded, and to have three of his Fingers cut off, and so dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefully and barbarously cast him into the River <hi>Tyber,</hi> and withal degraded
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:199119:30"/>all Persons that were ordain'd by him.</p>
            <p>During the time of the Popes <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, <hi>Honorius, Celistine, Innocent</hi> the fourth, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth, against <hi>Frederick</hi> the second, there was a most horrid Slaughter made by them, that lasted for thirty three Years. And then it was that <hi>Mahomet,</hi> the Imposter, and invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Enemy of Christianity, advanced himself in the East; whom the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour intended to repulse; but that the good Pope in that juncture of time made War against him in <hi>Italy,</hi> which hast'ned his return, and made him leave <hi>Greece</hi> to be harass'd by the <hi>Turk;</hi> nor would the Pope admit of a Reconciliation, till 11000 Marks of Gold procur'd it. And with the same zeal Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> and his Successors acted all along, who kept <hi>Zemin Ottoman, Bajazet</hi> the second's Brother, in custody, for which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd annually 40000 Ducats. Nay, when King <hi>Charles</hi> the eighth would have made an advantage of the Prisoners in his War against this mortal Foe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendom,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:199119:30"/>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the sixth advertis'd the <hi>Turk</hi> of his intended Designs (like a good Pope) and took such care to prevent him, that <hi>Zemin</hi> was poisoned; (an Action which a <hi>Mufti</hi> would scorn to do unto a Christian) for which good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and godly Work, he was rewarded with 200000 Crowns, which were paid him by <hi>George</hi> of <hi>Antia,</hi> the Messenger of that wholsome advice. By these fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Works we may guess at the Bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy temper of these Sanguinary Popes; and the best and truest Character we can bestow on them is that shameful by-word of young <hi>Tiberius,</hi> that the Pope is <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum sanguine maceratum,</hi> a mere Lump of Clay kneaded together with Blood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> the thirteenth was addicted to all manner of vices, as Perjury, Sacriledge, and Cruelty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He dismemb'red seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Cardinals, because they inclined to <hi>Otho</hi> the Great, Emperour, by Exoculating them, cutting off their Hands, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strating of them. He made Deacons in his Stable, among his Horses, like a Brute as he was; created young Boys grave
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:199119:31"/>Bishops, for Money, out of a lucrative and sordidly covetous Humour; whose Gehazisme and Simony, with some other Com-Popes of the Holy See, was the occasion of that known Distich;
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>An Petrus fuerat Romae sub Judice lis est,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Simonem Romae nemo fuisse negat.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whether St. <hi>Peter</hi> 'ere to <hi>Rome</hi> did go</l>
                  <l>Is question'd, that <hi>Simon</hi> was there, all know.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>He put out the eyes of his Ghostly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Benedict,</hi> and committed many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matchless Cruelties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Boniface</hi> the seventh was so wicked, that <hi>Baronius</hi> himself, that Grand Pillar of the Papal Cause, saith, he deserv'd the name of Thief and Murderer of his Countrey rather than of a Pope.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hildebrand</hi> sainted <hi>Liberius</hi> the <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> exercised all sorts of Cruelty, cut off the Foot of a Widows Son, but at last, for the Impieties which he was guilty of, (many of which are premention'd) he was depos'd in a Senate at <hi>Brixia;</hi> and as
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:199119:31"/>he lived wretchedly, so he died misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in Exile, and left the Keys to <hi>Victor</hi> the third, an <hi>Italian,</hi> thrust in by <hi>Matil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> who was soon poyson'd by his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon in the Chalice; so that you may see Christ's pretious Blood is no Antidote nor Preservative in these Cases.</p>
            <p>But this is only Slaughter by retail, take a view of their Massacres by whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sail.</p>
            <p>As to the Cruelties of <hi>Merindol</hi> and <hi>Cabriere,</hi> they were so barbarous and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane, that when the Advocate <hi>Aubery,</hi> and other Civilians, related them in the High Court of Parliament at <hi>Paris,</hi> the Auditory stopt their Ears at the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deousness, and horror of them: take this single Example for instance among many others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Menier,</hi> Lord of <hi>Oppede,</hi> Chief President of the Parliament of <hi>Provence,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King's Lieutenant Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral; who, tho he made choice of the worst Blood-hounds of the Army, could not meet with Soldiers cruel enough to execute his bloody Edicts, commanding
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:199119:32"/>them to rip up the Bowels of big-bellied Women, and to trample their innocent Babes under foot; and this was done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Face to his delight, who was then Spectator and Author of this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanity. This was a piece of cruelty beyond that of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to the male Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Women in the old, or the other of <hi>Herod</hi> to the Innocents of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> in the new Testament, and yet promoted and approv'd of by the Holy Man of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Parisian</hi> Massacre was so detesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and unparallel'd a Cruelty, according to <hi>Thuanus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thuan. Hist. l.</hi> 52. <hi>&amp;</hi> 53.</note> that some curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Persons perusing the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of other Nations, could not meet with the like in all Antiquity. The manner of this hellish and bloody Persecution, was as you find it in this ensuing Relation. <hi>Catharina di Medici,</hi> the Daughter of Pope <hi>Clement</hi>'s Brother, and Mother to <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth, did Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the Kingdom of <hi>France</hi> during the King's Minority, through the supine negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of <hi>Anthony</hi> King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> with
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:199119:32"/>whom the said Queen's Mother was joyned in the office of Protectorship, contrary to the Salique Law, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies the Inheritance, or Administration of the Realm to the Spindle. And she persuaded her Son to this Massacre. It was very speciously carryed on, and veil'd with pretences of the greatest Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty imaginable, and that was a Match be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Houses of <hi>Valois</hi> and <hi>Bourbon,</hi> the King resolving to bestow his Sister <hi>Margaret</hi> in marriage to Prince <hi>Henry,</hi> Son to <hi>Joan,</hi> Queen of <hi>Navarre,</hi> the former being a <hi>Romanist,</hi> the latter of the Religion. But before the Nuptials were Celebrated, the Queen of <hi>Navarre</hi> (being then at the Court of <hi>Paris,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding all things necessary for the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding-Solemnity) was poison'd by <hi>Renat,</hi> an <hi>Italian,</hi> the King's Apothecary, with the venomous scent of a pair of persum'd Gloves; by whose unnatural death, the Kingdom descended to the said <hi>Henry,</hi> precontracted to the King's Sister. Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the Marriage was solemniz'd with Royal Pomp and State in the chief Church
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:199119:33"/>at <hi>Paris,</hi> to the great joy of his Majesty and all good Men; to this wedding the Grandees of the Protestant party were courteously invited, <hi>viz. Henry</hi> Prince of <hi>Conde, Gasper de Coligni</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral of <hi>France,</hi> and Cousin to the King, <hi>Francis de Andelot,</hi> the Admiral's Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Captain of the Infantry, and other Princes and Nobles. And the Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, Jollity, and Caresses of Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were so great as are not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed. Nothing is seen but Banquets, Balls, Masques, Stage-Plays, and such kind of Divertisments, all personated in the Night. And this was the reason the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral had a desire to quit <hi>Paris,</hi> because he could not have accesse to the King, who was altogether taken up and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with these nocturnal Revels. But those of the reformed Religion hearing of his purpose to depart, with all speed delivered their Petitions to him for redress of Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, begging of him not to quit the place till he had presented them to the King, which he did on the 22<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust</hi> 1572, being the fifth day after the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:199119:33"/>Marriage. Returning home about noon, a Harquebuzier shot the Admiral with a brace of Bullets through both the Armes, out of the Window of a near adjoyning House; but the Villain made his escape, before they could reach the House. The King was then at Tennis with the Duke, when one of the Admiral's Gentlemen acquainted him with the news; which he no sooner heard, but he, with a seeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly violent Transport of Passion, threw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his Racket, and retir'd to his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle: as young as he was he made good use of the Motto of <hi>Lewis</hi> the 11<seg rend="sup">th</seg> his Predecessor, <hi>Qui nescit dissimulare, nescit regnare.</hi> The King swears most desperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, severely to revenge this injury; grants the Admiral a Guard at his request, but such a one as would be sure to ruine ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than secure him: and <hi>Cossin,</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Guards, was the Man that commanded them; a most Inveterate and Irreconcileable Enemy to the Admiral and his Party, and a fast friend to the <hi>Guisians.</hi> The Admiral hear's a noise and ratling of Armour, tho altogether
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:199119:34"/>undisturb'd, having the King's Royal word for his security; Besides, he reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Oath for Peace publiquely and frequently sworn by the King, his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Mother, the League with Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Articles with the Prince of <hi>Aurange</hi> to that purpose; the King's faith ingaged to the <hi>German</hi> Princes; some Towns taken in the low Countries by the King's order; his Sisters marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age celebrated but six days before (yet her Bridal Robes were stain'd and defil'd with innocent Blood) the judgment of foreign Princes, succeeding Posterity; the honour and Faith of a Prince, and the violation of the Law of Nations; all these, one would think, might easily oblige a Man to beleive that it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible he could ever assent to so out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious and monstrous a Fact.</p>
            <p>Well, notwithstanding all those Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testations, Promises, Oaths, and Vows, the Queen-Mother and the King had resolv'd upon a general Massacre through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the City of <hi>Paris,</hi> and this bloody Butchery was to be executed on the 24<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:199119:34"/>of <hi>August</hi> being Sunday (no matter for that, the better day the better deed) and accordingly it was perform'd: for <hi>Cossin</hi> first brake in, which the Admiral under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, caus'd those few Servants that were with him to lift him out of his Bed, for he could not rise without help, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so disabled by his Wounds, and put on a Night-gown, desiring them to make their escape, he himself resolving to dy with an undaunted Courage and Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an-like Resolution.</p>
            <p>These Assassines soon gain'd the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral's Chamber, broke open the doors, and <hi>Benvese,</hi> a <hi>German</hi> Miscreant, educated in the House of the Duke of <hi>Guise,</hi> with <hi>Cossin</hi> the <hi>Gascoign,</hi> and others, rush'd in with Swords, Targets, and Coats of Male. <hi>Benvese</hi> presenting his Sword to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral, after he had first blasphem'd God, ran him in the breast, and then cowardly struck the aged Gentleman on the Head; <hi>Attin</hi> Shot him with a Pistol, and <hi>Benvese</hi> gave him the third Wound on the Thigh, and so he fell down Dead upon the Spot. The Duke of <hi>Guise</hi> that staid in the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:199119:35"/>Court call'd to him and bid him throw him out at the window, which he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly did. Then he commanded the sign to be given by ringing the Tock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sein, or great Bell of the Palace, (which is never done but on extraordinary oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions:) the mark whereby the Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers were distinguished was by a general consent to be a white linnen Cloth tied about their Arm, and a white Cross on their Caps. Then an <hi>Italian</hi> Souldier of Captain <hi>Lewis Gonzagua</hi>'s, Duke of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> cut off the Admiral's Head, and sent it to <hi>Rome,</hi> preserv'd with Spices, to the Pope and Cardinal of <hi>Lorrain;</hi> others cut off his Hands, and some, void of all modesty, his Privities. Then the rude Rabble, for three days together drew the dead Body, thus mangled and weltering in Gore, thorow the Streets, and afterwards out of the Town, to the common Gallows, and there hang'd it up by the Feet. In the <hi>interim</hi> the rest brake into the other Chambers of the House, and slaught'red all they met with; among others, there were two young Pages of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:199119:35"/>honour, of noble Birth, Count <hi>Roch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foucaut,</hi> and young <hi>Theligius,</hi> who was Guilty of no other crime, but being the Admiral's Son in Law. So they ran about from morning till night, ransack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 400 Houses, sparing neither Age, nor Sex, and threw the Bodies out of the windows, so that the Streets were strewed with murd'red Carcasses, and ran down with Blood.</p>
            <p>The next day the Butchery was renewed, those disperate Villains stripping the dead Bodies of their Garments, and throwing them into the River of <hi>Sein.</hi> Nor was their Blood-thirstiness yet quenched, for Messengers were sent Post to all Cities, commanding them to imitate <hi>Paris,</hi> and to kill all of the Religion. Many Women with Child, Ladies and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, Advocates, Physicians, and other eminent Men of Learning and Piety; among the rest <hi>Peter Ramus,</hi> and several Students, were assassinated, without Plea, Sentence or Condemnation. I must not omit one passage that deserves a margi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Asterism in blood, that is of <hi>Ma'sson
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:199119:36"/>de Rivers,</hi> a Pastor, and the first that laid the foundation of the Protestant Church at <hi>Paris. Mansorel,</hi> a mortal Enemy of the Religion, as soon as the Slaughter was began in <hi>Paris,</hi> was sent Post to <hi>Angiers</hi> to prevent the News of Massacre by others: as soon as he arriv'd there, he was conducted to <hi>Masson</hi>'s House; in the very Entry he meets with his Wife and there saluted her very cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniously (a right <hi>Judas</hi> kiss, for he came to betray her Master) he demanded where her Husband was, she replied in the Garden, and being brought to him they mutually and lovingly (as to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance) embraced each other, <hi>Mansorel</hi> told him in plain terms, like a bloody Butcher, I am come hither by the King's command to kill you, as you may perceive by these Letters, producing his Dague ready charged. <hi>Masson</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer'd, I have committed no Crime; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, I beg the favour of a little time to call upon God and recommend my self to his merciful hands. Which short Oraison being soon concluded, he with
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:199119:36"/>a meek Christian temper receiv'd his Death-Wound, being Shot through the Body; but to return to <hi>Paris.</hi> We left the Admiral's Body hang'd up; the <hi>Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sians</hi> went thither in great Multitudes, and the Queen Mother carried the King along with them and her other two Sons to glut their eyes with that barbarous Spectacle; but the next night the Body was convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away, and interr'd, as 'tis conjectur'd. Their cruelty not being yet satiated, they bring some to publique Tryal, to efface the blot of dishonour that might justly reflect upon the King; and there was a parcel of Judges call'd out for that very purpose, who made an Order that a man of Hay (since the Admiral's Body could not be found) should be made, and be dragg'd by the <hi>Boureau</hi> through the Streets, in Effigie, which was according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done, his Arms and Ensigns of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour broken, his Memory blasted, his Castles and Farms razed to the ground, his Issue declar'd Ignoble, Infamous, and Intestate, and all the Trees in his Woods to be cut down, to the height of six Foot.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:199119:37"/>
            <p> Thus in all Towns great Murthers were committed, but none more horrid or devillish than the Massacre at <hi>Lions, Mandolet</hi> being Governour. As soon as he received the Letters, he, by a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet and Cryer, summoned those of the Religion to appear before him, which they readily did. Then he committed them to several Prisons, and desir'd the common Executioner to call some to his assistance, and to murther them in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, but he refus'd it, saying, he execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Law on none but such as were publickly condemned, (a goodly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour indeed, more cruel than the common Hangman!) Upon this deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, he commanded the Garrison Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Castle to take upon them that worthy action, and they refus'd it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, upon a punctilio of Honour, that they did not use to fight with naked men; but the Butchers and Water-men at last (verifying the old Saying, that they are <hi>pessimum genus hominum</hi>) were the wretched Actors of his Bloody De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, committing unheard of Cruelties,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:199119:37"/>and sporting with them in the midst of their misery. Insomuch that the Blood which came out of the Goal, call'd the Arch-bishop's Prison, was seen in the day-time, to the horrour of the standers by, to flow reaking hot in the Channels of the Streets, and so into the River of <hi>Seine.</hi> Thus for the space of thirty days complete, there was no intermission of Murther and Slaughter all over <hi>France,</hi> so that there were about 100000 Persons slain. The
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Guignard,</hi> in his Oration, said, It was a great mistake that they did not cut the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>silisk Vein.</note> Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom and the Prince of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,</hi> who were secur'd, and turn'd Papists to escape their fury, yet could not avoid it; for the one was poison'd, and the other stab'd by the Papists. But now to the purpose. His Holiness surely could not but detest and abhorr such barbarous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanity; yet since this was done upon the account of Religion, and he is held to be the only competent Judge of it; let us give ear to his Opinion, which we find recorded in <hi>Thuanus,</hi> a Papist, and an Authentick Historiographer, <hi>Hist.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:199119:38"/>l.</hi> 53. The Pope's Legate at <hi>Paris</hi> gave him an exact Relation of this Massacre, which he received with great Joy and Satisfaction; read the Letter openly in the Consistory of Cardinals, and fell to consultation about the matter; where it was concluded and decreed, <hi>nemine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicente,</hi> that they should go to St. <hi>Mark</hi>'s Church, and return solemn thanks to God for so great a blessing bestowed on the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and the whole Christian World: and this being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that a <hi>Jubilee</hi> should be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with published throughout all Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to give thanks to the Almighty for destroying the Enemies of the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Guns were fir'd at the Castle of St. <hi>Angelo,</hi> Bonfires made, and all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrations of Joy manifested for this great Victory. Within a short time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, there was a Procession to St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> made by his Holiness, under a Canopy, his Train being born up by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour's Ambassadour, with many of the Clergy and Nobility: and an Inscripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was set over the Church door; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:199119:38"/>the Cardinal of <hi>Lorrain</hi> in the name of the <hi>French</hi> King congratulated his Holiness and the Cardinals, <hi>&amp;c. for the plainly stupendous effects, and altogether incredible events of the Counsels they gave him, of the Assistance they sent him, and of their twelve years desires and Prayers.</hi> Not long after the Pope sent Cardinal <hi>Ʋrsin</hi> to Congratulate the <hi>French</hi> King in his name; who in his journey highly extoll'd the zeal of those who had a hand in the Massacre, and very prodigally di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stributed the Pope's blessings among them; and at <hi>Paris</hi> he used these words; <hi>The remembrance of the late Action, to be mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified in all Ages, as conducing to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and the dignity of the holy Church of Rome, &amp;c.</hi> What could a <hi>Dionysius,</hi> or a <hi>Phalaris</hi> have said more to purpose? 'Twas nobly spoken, like a Man of God in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, one that in tended to make more use of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Sword than St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Keys to do the work of the Lord more effectually.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fifth, because he sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth of <hi>France</hi> to be an Heritick,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thu.</hi> Hist. <hi>l.</hi> 91.</note> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:199119:39"/>the <hi>Guisians</hi> (whom he stiled the <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabees</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) to enter into an holy League against their Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sovereign; calling in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Savoy</hi> to their Assistance, which Succors they paid off with the Rights of the Crown: and did all that in them lay to rob him, both of his Kingdom and Life; which forced this King to treat them as they had the Hugonots; and for standing thus manfully upon his own Legs, in his own defence, he is shamefully abused by one of the <hi>Romanists,</hi> a Man of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and shameless Brow, to bespatter a Puissant Monarch with such base and scurrilous Language: for he doth not blush to affirm, that he was 1000 times worse than <hi>Mahomet;</hi> nay, he goes farther, saying, that no Nation ever suffered such a Tyrant from the Creation to his time. <hi>Kos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saeus p.</hi> 17. However, the Pope Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates the King, grants an Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of nine Years, to any Subject that would fight against him, as the wages of his Rebellion; and did prognosticate (which he might easily doe without
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:199119:39"/>Necromancy, an Art that many of them have been very expert in) that it would not be long 'ere he came to a violent Death. The Subjects take up Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their King, and earn the Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; and a Friar with his Knife vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the Prediction: and the exultation and joy that was at <hi>Rome</hi> for this Assassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, can hardly be believ'd, were it not warranted by the Popes Harangue to his Cardinals, printed at <hi>Paris</hi> 1589, wherein he saith, this work of God (the King's murther) is to be compar'd with the Incarnation and Resurrection of Christ for it's Stupendiousness; and prefers the <hi>Friar's</hi> courage and fervent zeal to God, before that of <hi>Eleazar</hi> and <hi>Judith,</hi> aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that the King died in the Sin against the Holy Ghost, tho a profest Papist. Thus a Popish King is stab'd, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd to Hell for sparing the Blood of Hugonots.</p>
            <p>I will not trouble you with the story of the Spanish Invasion in eighty eight, in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> nor the Gun-powder Plot in the time of King
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:199119:40"/>
               <hi>James,</hi> tho the former was plotted, counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced, and abetted by Pope <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and the latter had it's rise from the Breves of Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the eighth; (for where shall you hear of any monstrous Design that his Holiness hath not a Hand in?) These wicked Practices are so modern, and well known, that, I presume, the Reader wants not a Remembrancer to put him in mind of them, but my Pen is almost choakt up with Blood and Gore; therefore I will conclude these Tragedies with this Epilogue, made ready to my hand, on the deplored death of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Jane Gray.</hi>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nescio tu quibus es Lector lecturus ocellis,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hoc scio quod siccis scribere non potui.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I know not, Reader, how you can for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear,</l>
                     <l>I'me sure I could not write without a Tear.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The next thing that falls under our consideration is, the Popes Heavenly-mindedness, Knowledge, Learning, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, Infalibility, and some other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:199119:40"/>
            <p> As to the first, to shew how heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they are inclin'd; <hi>Baronius and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebrard,</hi> both mortal Enemies to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, and great Promoters of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Interest and Religion, cannot but confess ingeniously, without any provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation thereunto, that from the Year 870, to the Year 1050, none sate in the Papal Chair, but such as were Necromancers, Magicians, Adulterers, Murtherers and Impious Persons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hildebrand</hi> was a notorious Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cromancer, raised Devils familiarly, shook sparks of Fire out of his sleeve by Magick Art, being elected by Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, contrary to the Canons of the Church, and when he obtain'd the Papacy, play'd the Devil for Gods sake, expell'd Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals at his pleasure, and supported him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self by his Sorcery and Witchcraft.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> thirteenth, <hi>Monstrum Papae,</hi> a monster of a Pope, he, besides other fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and enormous crimes which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, call'd for the Devil to assist him at Dice, and after drank a Health to him, and, like a Devil incarnate, would ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:199119:41"/>about and break Windows, fire Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses in the night, and run away by the light of them.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Sylvester</hi> the second, was a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cromancer, and gave his Soul to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, by compact made with him, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he might obtain the Popedom. This is strange, tho true, to part with that for mony, that cannot be purchas'd with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; sure he had but a very bad Bargain on't.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the sixth, was guilty of Witchcraft as well as Incest, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catenation of other Crimes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> the third was a Magician, as well as <hi>John</hi> the 8th, 12th, 13th, 14th, 15th, 16th, 17th, as if the name, whose Ety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mology implies Gracious, could be so im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure and satanical; and you will find, if you consult their own Authors, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in a <hi>Marcelline,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Platina in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Marcelli.</note> Arrianisme in a <hi>Liberius,</hi> Diabolical Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications and Inhumations in a wicked <hi>Celestine,</hi> and such barbarous Cruelties, that Paganism it self, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritively merciful, and Mahometism mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally vertuous.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:199119:41"/>
            <p> Their Learning and Knowledge in the Arts and Sciences will appear in a Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the second, who was brought up a Merchant's Factor, and was so great a hater of Learning and the Learned, that he pronounced them Hereticks, who durst so much as name the word Academy,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Platina in vit. Paul.</hi> 2.</note> either in jest or earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est: Nay farther, my Author saith, <hi>Hunc ob rem Romanos ad hortaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ne filios diutius in studiis literarum paterentur; satis esse si legere &amp; scribere potuissent;</hi> therefore he advis'd the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> not to suffer their Children to go to School any longer, than till they had learnt to write and read.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calixtus</hi> the third, an old decrepit foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish <hi>Spaniard,</hi> of whom Cardinal <hi>Pontanus de magni, c.</hi> 12. of his Election, <hi>Quam fatue, fatui, fatuum creavere Calixtum.</hi> How foolishly did the fools elect thee, fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish <hi>Calixtus,</hi> to the Papacy?</p>
            <p>The poor Bishop <hi>Virgilius,</hi> a <hi>German</hi> Mathematician, was cited to <hi>Rome</hi> for an Heretick, because he asserted the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podes,</hi> and there (as one hath it) by
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:199119:42"/>the fiery zeal of Pope <hi>Zachary,</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<q>to the Flames, to shew how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible the <hi>Roman</hi> Oracle is in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning that which all do maintain; and himself maintain'd the <hi>Antipodes</hi> in his life, his footsteps being opposite to those of his meek and pious An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Some Popes have been mere ignorant Lay-men at their Election.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Boniface</hi> the ninth, a <hi>Neopolitan,</hi> was so illiterate, that he could neither write, sing, nor say, (a fit Person to be Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal Pastor, and to instruct the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant) nor understand matters discuss'd before him; yet a notable Huckster for selling Livings, who expos'd all to sale; no Dolt could be long unpreferr'd if he came open-handed, and could purchase with money.</p>
            <p>One of the <hi>Benedicts</hi> was a Boy of ten years of age, a Popeling, not manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted from the rigour of the <hi>ferula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; John</hi> the 13th, an aged Stripling of nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen: Nay, some Popes, as <hi>Alphonsus de Castro</hi> intimates, were such Learned Clerks,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:199119:42"/>
               <hi>ut penitus Grammaticam ignorarent,</hi> that they had scarce read their Grammar. What? beardless Striplings ascend the Chair! surely 'tis not come to that yet! but it is, assure your self, whatever is the matter. Hence we may rationally infer, that that Church must needs be well ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nag'd that hath such Reverend Guides and Learned Heads, yet if you look about you, you'l find more in't than you imagine; 'tis very probable these Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors of St. <hi>Peter</hi> did it to avoid the imputation of St. <hi>Paul; Too much Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hath made thee mad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take a spice of their Sobriety in Pope <hi>Benedict</hi> the 12th, who was so great a Drinker, would carouze so briskly, and turn off his Cups so merrily, that it seems he deserv'd this Epitaph, which some good Fellow or other bestow'd on him: the <hi>Latin</hi>'s honest, but homely.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iste fuit vero Laicis mors vipera Clero,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Devius à vero, Cupa repleta mero.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He was to Lay-men death in sooth,</l>
               <l>To Clergy and Divines</l>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:199119:43"/>
               <l>A Viper; deviating from truth;</l>
               <l>A mere Hogshead of Wines.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Well, I'll say this for him, and a Fig for him, he was a boon blade I'll war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant you; this is the only sociable Pope that we have met with in the whole crew hitherto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Innocent</hi> the eighth, a dull ignorant Sot, who would take a Cup too much in the midst of his Affairs of greatest weight and importance, and like a true Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher drink till his head run round with the World, in vindication of the <hi>Coper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nican</hi> Systeme.</p>
            <p>Their Conversation of yea, yea, and nay, nay, they observe very perfunctori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for the Laity and inferiour Clergy out-hector the whole World in blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and customary Oaths; nor are the Popes themselves free from this vain Vice, that is neither sweetned with Pleasure nor season'd With Profit.</p>
            <p>The Barons of <hi>England,</hi> seeing that the Kingdom and Crown was become ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely tributary to the Pope, to their
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:199119:43"/>great grief and perplexity, demanded some Priviledges of King <hi>John,</hi> which he had engaged by Oath to grant; to which he return'd no answer, but referr'd them wholly to Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, as his Liege-Lord of whom he held his Crown. Ambassadors were sent to <hi>Rome,</hi> with Instructions and Demands to that purpose: but his Holiness resented it so ill, that in the close of his Speech, he Swore, with a furrow'd Brow, by Saint <hi>Peter</hi> I cannot suffer this injury to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punished. Boldly done <hi>Innocent!</hi> 'Twas more than St. <hi>Peter</hi> himself durst do, had he then sate in the Chair. And ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, upon some occasion being mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to Passion, he Swore by St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> both, that neither of them might take exceptions; of whom one wrote this Distich.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> the worst of all the rout,</l>
               <l>If you would spell his name right, put <hi>In</hi> out.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Grosthead,</hi> the honest Bishop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> opposed Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> and laught at his thundring Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:199119:44"/>of whom it is reported, that he came to him after his death, and put his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in mind, by a blow with his Crosier, of this Item, <hi>Surge miser, &amp; veni in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicum Dei:</hi> and soon after he died of a Plurisie.</p>
            <p>Now for the Grand <hi>Palladium</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> their so much boasted of, and highly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded infallibity, which is infeof'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, tho the Pope be Heretick, Idolater, Incestuous, a Necro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancer, Sodomite, nay, what not, if he once claps his Apostolik Seat there, he must necessarily be free from error.</p>
            <p>Doctor <hi>John Funecius,</hi> a Man of great Learning, in the 10th Book of his Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nology reports, that in the year 1332 Pope <hi>John</hi> the 22th, fell into a great He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie, which was this; That the Souls de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted this life, did not injoy the Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical Vision, that is see God, till the last day; yet this Pope must be infallible, tho guilty of so gross an Error.</p>
            <p>There hapned a great difference between this Pope and the <hi>Franciscans;</hi> he char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them with Heresie, and they again, to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:199119:44"/>requite his kindness, disowning him, as a damnable Heretick, and no Pope; thus his Infallibility of Judgment is disclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his own Crew, and he himself un-Pop'd by them.</p>
            <p>There were three blazing Comets con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicuous in the <hi>Roman</hi> Horizon at one and the same time, that was in the 11th Century, <hi>viz. Benedict</hi> the 9th, <hi>Sylvester</hi> the third, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the sixth, and, as one saith very well, It were very strange if they should produce no alteration in the Ecclesiastical Body. Three Popes cohabiting at <hi>Rome,</hi> and as many more residing in three several Countries; a Grand Schism for the space of forty years; and Ambition and Corruption, being more prevalent to advance to the Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical Dignity, than a good Christian Life. It must needs be a greater Prodigy, than a Miracle-monger, by the help of his forged Legends, can pretend to, that contrariety should meet and shake hands, and absolute Contradictions prove a Pope infallible. These were Anti-Popes in competition and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:199119:45"/>to the Papal Promotion; nay, their own Authors are at difference, yet a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> daggers drawn about his infallibility. See <hi>Gerson, Occham, Alimain, Ecchins, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sins, Pighins</hi> and <hi>Waldensis.</hi> Nay, the prettiest humour of all is, that they should impose upon us so much as to force us to believe, that when two Popes contradict each other, yet they are both infallible, or if they enjoyn the perusal of different Bibles we must use neither.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Ʋrban</hi> the 8th liv'd the longest and died the richest of all the Popes; for he sat in the Chair twenty years: a rare thing (for they usually kick up their heels very suddenly, and the reason is this, if they should live long they would do too much mischief) tho none of them ever attain'd to the years of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> who, as they say, was Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> twenty five. This <hi>Ʋrban</hi> was a very active Man, and did not only pry into the present Affairs of the Church, but with a retrospect did rip up and dive into old matters; to which end and purpose he appointed a select Committee to examine Accounts, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:199119:45"/>take cognizance of the Errors of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors; upon which occasion this witty Pasquin was made at <hi>Rome;</hi> where there are the Statues of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> erected upon a Bridge there directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite one to the other, a merry wag had clapt a pair of Spurs upon St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s heels, and St. <hi>Paul</hi> is supposed to say to him, Whither so fast in this riding posture? who answers him; I apprehend there is great danger in my stay at <hi>Rome,</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of this new Commission, for I fear they will question me for denying my Master, therefore I'll post away to some other place of Safety; and truly Brother <hi>Peter,</hi> said <hi>Paul,</hi> I intend not to stay long after you, for I have as much reason to suspect that they will examine me for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuting Christians before my Conversion.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Zachary,</hi> when the trade of Church-merchandizes was very dead, and he had little or nothing to do, rather than he would be idle, wrote to Bishop <hi>Boniface</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> directions when to eat Bacon, and he did very well in't, whatsoever the prating Hugonot says to
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:199119:46"/>the contrary; tho he had done far better, in the Opinion of some of our modern Casuists, if he had also given him some wholsom Instructions concerning the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation of Eggs, that so the Prelate might have had a complete Dish.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth had an intention to create <hi>Raphael Ʋrbin,</hi> a mere Painter, Cardinal; And why might not a good Painter make a good Cardinal? but sure it was not he who drew the Pictures of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and made them so red-faced, that that he was reprov'd for it by some of the Conclave, because the ignorant might be apt to judge them great Drinkers, to the scandal of Religion; but he soon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, that is your mistake and not mine; for I made them so ruddy, because I knew that if they were living they would blush for shame at the vicious lives of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Successors. Now what if it were the same Man? It was great and good Policie in the Pope, beyond the reach of a Protestant Noddle; for hereby he might oblige all of that Profession, in hopes of the like Promotion, that when
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:199119:46"/>ever any of them for the future should undertake to draw the Pourtraicture of any Saint whatsoever, he should make them of a more pallid and sober Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion. I'll warrant you this leering Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not laughs in his sleeve at this pretty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue of Church-Policy: but no matter for that, the Papist cries out, Let him laugh that wins, and so gives you one Proverb in exchange of another.</p>
            <p>It is reported in our History, that King <hi>James</hi> of blessed Memory did once in his Progress vouchsafe to bestow a visit upon Sir — <hi>Pope,</hi> Knight, whose Lady at that time was lately deliver'd of a Daughter, and the Infant was presented to his Majesty with a Paper of Verses in her Hand which the King was much pleas'd with, the Contents whereof were as followeth;
<q>
                  <l>See this little Mistris here,</l>
                  <l>Who ne're sate in <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair,</l>
                  <l>Or a Triple Crown did wear,</l>
                  <l>And yet she is a Pope;</l>
                  <l>She hardly is a seven-night old,</l>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:199119:47"/>
                  <l>Nor did she ever hope</l>
                  <l>To Saint one with a Pope,</l>
                  <l>And yet she is a Pope.</l>
                  <l>No Benefices she e're sold;</l>
                  <l>Nor did dispence with Sins for Gold;</l>
                  <l>No King her Feet did ever kiss,</l>
                  <l>Or had from her worse look than this,</l>
                  <l>And yet she is a Pope.</l>
                  <l>A Female Pope you'l say, a second <hi>Joan;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nay, sure she is Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> or none.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now if any or all your Romanists can, out of your long <hi>Nomenclatura</hi> of Popes, produce one that may come near this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Pope for Innocence, Modesty, or Humility, wee'l save you the labour of compassing Sea and Land to make Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selytes, for wee'l all unanimously return, and without any more adoe re-unbosom our selves with your Holy Mother the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is thought by some, and those Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Persons too, that <hi>Pasqin,</hi> among the many witty Jests he hath thrown up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Pope and Clergy, never acted any thing with better Grace, than when
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:199119:47"/>he counterfeited himself so affronted that he was ready to die for very Grief, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he had receiv'd such an Injury as had almost broke his very Heart: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing askt by one that heard him bemoan himself; what Injury, Friend, is this that is done to thee? Has any one call'd thee Thief or Buggerer? No, no, said he. What then? And so went on naming most of the grossest Indignities that could be put upon a Man by opprobrious Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. No, no, pish, said he, you have not hit it yet; and so breaking out into grievous Sobs and Sighs, Alas! alas! said he, 'tis worse then all you can imagine, they have been so abusive as to call me Pope. Nay farther, he has given you to understand what conceit he and all Men should have of the Pope, by this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hexastick.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hic Carapha jacet Superis invisus &amp; Imis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Styx animam; Tellus putre cadaver habet.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Invidit paçem Terris, Diis Vota Precesque,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Impius, &amp; Clerum perdidit, &amp; Populum.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:199119:48"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hostibus infensis supplex, infidus amicis:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Scire cupis paucis caetera? Papa fuit.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here th' hate of Heaven and Hell, <hi>Carapha</hi> lies:</l>
               <l>Ith' Grave's his Body; in <hi>Styx</hi> his Soul cries:</l>
               <l>He envied Peace with Men and Prayers to God;</l>
               <l>To Lay and Clergy-men a wicked Rod.</l>
               <l>Suppliant to Foes; but Faithless to his Friend:</l>
               <l>In short, he was a Pope, and there's an End.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the 10th, being told by his Confessor, that he need fear nothing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he had the Keys of Heaven at his Girdle, and those of the Church Treasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry also, consisting in the Merits of Christ, and the blessed Saints, gave him this true answer. Thou know'st that he who hath once sold a thing, hath no longer right to it; therefore, since I have made sale of Heaven and all to others, I have nothing to do with it my self; which being the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:199119:48"/>common Traffick at <hi>Rome,</hi> was the occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this saying.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Roma dat omnibus omnia dantibus, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia Romae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cum pretio.</hi> —</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> gives to all that part with all their Gold:</l>
               <l>For there all things are merely bought and sold.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The same Pope being reproved by some of his Cardinals, for leading so leud a Life, being grown worse and worse, since his Inauguration; answer'd them, If I am wicked you are the cause of it, for you made me what I am; which strange reply, put them to this question, what he meant by saying so; why, quoth he, you have made me Pope, and it is impossible to be a Pope and a good Man; Now this must needs be infallibly true, because Infallibility it self, maintains it to be so.</p>
            <p>Thus you see what it is to be a Pope, and may rest satisfied with this as a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rollary for all; if horrid Blasphemies, Oathes, and Execrations; if filthy Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Adultery, Incest, Sodomy and Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery;
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:199119:49"/>if intolerable Pride, Ambition, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and Oppression; if bloody Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Butcheries, Murthers and Massacres; if sordid Avarice, Simony and Sacriledge, if Hellish Sorcery, Witchcraft, and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cromancy; if blockish Ignorance, Stupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, Gaming, and all manner of Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries; if these or any of these are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable and sufficient Qualifications for the Papacy, then no Persons in the World were ever more fit to govern the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> than those Popes that we have given you an Account of; but it is now high time to take our leave, and bid them all Adieu.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sic explicit Actus primus. Exit</hi> Pope, Enter Cardinal.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Cardinals, Abbots, Bishops, and Jesuits promiscuously.</head>
               <p>ANd first of the Cardinals, being next to the Pope, and Superior to others in Dignity; let us observe whether the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals Cap shrowds as many Vices as the Triple Crown; but here I must tell you for your Comfort before hand, that
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:199119:49"/>you'l find ne're a Barrel better Herring but like Master like Man; like Head like Members; and those as bad as bad can be, nay, which is worst of all, 'tis a stark shame, that there is no shame among them.</p>
               <p>The Popes have been Fathers to some, but <hi>Silvester</hi> the first was Godfather to all of them: for by him they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Cardinals. <hi>qd. Cardines,</hi> because they are the Persons about whom, like Hinges, the Church Militant ought to move, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose upon, and be supported; to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate unto us, that those who attain to the Dignity of the Cardinalate, ought to be so Exemplary in their Lives and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versations, that all Christians may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated by their Actions, and the very Infidels perswaded to return into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>som of the Roman Catholick and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolick Church; Who, when he is cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated by the Pope's Breve, 'tis in these Words; <hi>Creamus te Socium Regibus, su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periorem Ducibus &amp; Fratrem nostrum.</hi> We do make thee equal to Kings, Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to Dukes, and our own Brother. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> the fourth gave them the red Hat,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:199119:50"/>
                  <hi>Boniface</hi> the ninth their Vestment, and <hi>Paul</hi> the second the Scarlet Cap, to sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie unto us how ready they are to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their Lives and shed their Blood for the Honour of God, and Service of their holy Mother the Church, or which is more probable, to spill the Blood of those good Christians who oppose their superstitious and idolatrous Worship; Now, how they deserve either Name or Habit bestow'd on them by his Holiness, whose Infallibility is as much to be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion'd in this, as in any other Matter, these ensuing Relations will soon convince you.</p>
               <p>And first, for their blasphemous and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Expressions and abuses of Scripture; for we will be more plain with them than their Universal Bishop, and not cloak Vice with the name of Virtue.</p>
               <p>Cardinal <hi>Bembo</hi> was so much affected with, and tied up to <hi>Cicero,</hi> that he would use none but his Words: therefore the Senate of <hi>Venice</hi> must be stil'd, <hi>Patres con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scripti,</hi> Dukes and Dukedoms, <hi>Reges &amp; Regna,</hi> the grand <hi>Turk</hi> and the <hi>Sophi,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:199119:50"/>Reges Armeniae &amp; Thracum:</hi> Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, <hi>Interdictio Igni &amp; Aquae;</hi> Faith, <hi>Persuasio;</hi> Nuns, Vestals; and the Pope <hi>Pontifex Maximus,</hi> and he was so puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed up with this Conceit, that he altogether slighted St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epistles, abusing them with the Name of <hi>Epistolacciae,</hi> little idle Epistles, disswading his Friends from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>usal of them, lest thereby they should corrupt their Eloquence. 'Twas done like a true Christian Cardinal, to prefer <hi>Cicero</hi> the <hi>Pagan,</hi> before St <hi>Paul</hi> the learned and great Apostle of the Gentiles.</p>
               <p>And another Popish Prelate had so great a stock of Impudence as to say, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> penn'd many unnecessary things, which might have been better omitted; and farther, that if he had seriously con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered the offence that might afterwards have been given thereby, he would have been better advis'd, before he had ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured upon the Publication of them.</p>
               <p>Cardinal <hi>Baronius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baron. in his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition against the</hi> Venetians, <hi>p.</hi> 47.</note> in his Discourse against the Seignory of <hi>Venice,</hi> blames the <hi>Venetians</hi> in these proud and profane
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:199119:51"/>words, <hi>The</hi> Venetians <hi>doing the contrary are as Monsters and Prodigies of the De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vil;</hi> adding this reason to corroborat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and strengthen his Argument, and setting himself above the Angels, to prove hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> authority over them; <hi>Know ye not that we shall judge the Angels?</hi> Abusing that Scripture, and wresting it for his own ends, whereas it speaks of all the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, (not Clergy-men solely) who shall sit as Assistants to our Saviour at the last day, when he shall pronounce, <hi>Goe ye cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,</hi> &amp;c. against the wicked Sinners.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is so bold as to affirm, that the Pope is Head of the Church,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar. l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Pon. c. q.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Etiam Christo secluso,</hi> though contrary to the Holy Gospel, <hi>I am with you alway, unto the end of the World:</hi> and in opposition to their own Canons: which says expressly; <hi>Christ is always the Governour and Head of his Body,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gl. v. non. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonam Clem. Ne Romam l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Elect. tit.</hi> 3.</note> viz; <hi>the Church, and although the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car fail, yet he doth never fail it.</hi> It is reported by an <hi>Italian</hi> Writer, that a Cardinal lying upon his
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:199119:51"/>death-bed, desired to be shriven; and when his Confessor came to do that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, he told him that he must worship one God only; who replied so I do, and that God is the Pope: for since his Holiness is God on Earth, (and two Gods are not to be worshipped) I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adore the visible than the invisible Deity: the Confessor rejoyn'd, the Pope is neither God nor Christ, but the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal clos'd the discourse with this Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, I would have thee to understand, that if Christ were alive again, and should take a Journey to <hi>Rome,</hi> the Pope would give him a very cold (or no) reception, unless he would humble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self so far as to kiss his Pantofle.</p>
               <p>It was the devout saying of a profound Doctor of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, who did declare openly, that if he were satisfied no Person had St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epistles but himself, he would commit them to the flames, and burn them, rather than they should be publikly Read.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:199119:52"/>
               <p> Next, of their Riches, Lasciviousness, and Incontinency.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baptista Fulgosius,</hi> though a great stick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler for Popery,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fulgos. l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> reports of <hi>Peter Riarius,</hi> one of Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth's Cardinals, that his Gownes, the Tieks, and Coverings of his Bed, were all of Cloth of Gold, and his other Furniture of Silk, and that he feasted <hi>Elianor</hi> of <hi>Arragon,</hi> as she was on her Journey to <hi>Hercules d'Este,</hi> Duke of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> with whom she was to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried very sumptuously, I had almost said Royally, where there was such variety, and different sorts of Luxurious Viands, and Delicious Quelqueschoses, that the Banquet continued seven hours, and that his Guests might not be tired with so long and tedious a Treat, he diverted them with several Plays, which were acted whilst they sate at Table, and every Servitor that attended, to render the Entertainment more splendid, had a new Sute every Course that was brought in; this is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Proverb, Prelates fare
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:199119:52"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndeed, that is delicious Food; yet all this is short of what he says afterwards, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat he was so shameless as to keep his Whore <hi>Tiresia,</hi> publickly, and so splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly rich in all her gorgeous Apparel, that her very Shooes were studded with Diamonds, Pearls, and pretious Stones.</p>
               <p>The great and modest Prelate, <hi>John</hi> Bishop of <hi>Crema,</hi> who was commissiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to oppose the Marriage of the English Clergy, did perform his errand so well as to confute himself grosly; for that very night he was taken in Bed with a Strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet. What of all this? you must not take notice of what they do, but what they say, thus the Catholicks excuse it, but I'le warrant you the Hugonot will either laugh, or shake his head at such frivolous and sinful Evasions.</p>
               <p>At the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> (a fit place for such an Action) a Husband lent his Wife to a Cardinal (see what Fripperers and Brokers they are, that can pawn their Wives Chastity for filthy lucre) and though at first she was religiously scrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, pleading Conscience, yet she soon
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:199119:53"/>alter'd her Mind, and prostituted her Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to the holy Man's Embraces. The next Morning the Cardinal's Concubine went very confidently to her Husband, and paid him the Mony promis'd for her work; telling him withall, that though you take it but for a Loan, yet assure your self it is an absolute sale, therefore you had best provide your self another Bed-fellow; for to tell you the Truth, I had rather be sold out right, then bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lent, that I may not be put to the trouble of changing so often.</p>
               <p>There was a Bishop who said these Words in the hearing of the Writer;
<note place="margin">Stevens <hi>Apol. for</hi> Heroditus.</note> In former times Clergy-Men were advanced for their Learning and Knowledge in the Tongues; but for his own particular he understood not one Syllable of Latin but his Passe-Latin (that is the Office of a Pander or Bawd) by which means he was promoted to the Episcopacy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John de la Casa,</hi> Arch-Bishop of <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent,</hi> and the Pope's Legate in the whole State of <hi>Venice,</hi> was the Author of an <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:199119:53"/>Poem, where he chanted forth 1000 <hi>Encomiums</hi> of <hi>Sodomy:</hi> among other Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thets which he gives it, he calls it a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Work; which Book was printed at <hi>Venice</hi> by <hi>Trojanus Nanus,</hi> as the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuenses</hi> that copied it out, do averr, <hi>Monstrum horrendum,</hi> &amp;c. A Monster of of Men.</p>
               <p>A certain Friar, summoned to appear before his Diocesan, being accus'd for a <hi>Lutheran,</hi> but he not only excus'd, but accquitted him, because he could wench, swear, be drunk, and did not quote Scripture; which true Story gave birth to this facetious Epigram,
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Esse Lutheranum rumor te, Gaurice, clamat; Sed tuus Antistes te tamen esse negat;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Tam Scortaris ait, quam si vel Episcopus esses,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Et potas dubiam pervigil usque Diem:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nec memor es Christi, nisi cum jurare libebit,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nec scis Scripturas, nec breve jota sacrae,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="98" facs="tcp:199119:54"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nempe per haec suevit nunqam fallentia signa</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ille vigil sanas noscere Pastor Oves.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Gauricus</hi> by report's a <hi>Lutheran,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>His ghostly Father says he's no such man,</l>
                        <l>Because he wenches at that wanton rate,</l>
                        <l>As if the Miter adorn'd his bald Pate,</l>
                        <l>He's such a fuddle Cap too, as they say,</l>
                        <l>He tipples without ceasing Night and Day.</l>
                        <l>Nor thinks on Christ, but when he's swearing Oaths,</l>
                        <l>Nor of the Holy Writ one tittle knows.</l>
                        <l>Now by such never failing Marks as these,</l>
                        <l>Which are his good Sheep th' watchful Pastor sees.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Cardinal <hi>Granvil</hi> was a debauch't Man, one of low Birth, but high Advancement, a Smith's Son; and we may well say of him, as <hi>Juvenal</hi> did of the <hi>Greek</hi> Orator of the same extract, in his 10th Satyr, who, though an Heathen, did exceed him as much in Morality as Rhetorick; and if his Lot had fallen within the Pale of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:199119:54"/>the Church, would undoubtedly have deserv'd the Cardinalate much more than he, and prov'd a better Christian.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A carbone &amp; forcipibus, gladiosque pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Incude, &amp; luteo Vulcano ad Rhetora missus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>The private part of this Cardinal's Life, his secret Retirements, and Closet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation, was dissolute and detestably las<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civious, even to Romanists themselves; the dimensions of his Immoralities and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties were of a vast extent; his Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, Lechery, and Wantonness banisht him from <hi>Rome, Naples</hi> and <hi>Millan:</hi> He, to promote his Lust, caused several exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site Pieces of obscenity to be drawn and printed, and in his private recesses he had the Pictures of the Greatest Ladies and Beauties pourtraicted to the Life, which had been by him violated, and prostituted to his devillish Lust; insomuch that there was a <hi>Pasquinata</hi> that went up and down of him and some others, that <hi>Carrera</hi>'s
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:199119:55"/>Cowardise, the Duke of <hi>Sesa</hi>'s Gout, <hi>Don John</hi>'s Cod-piss and Cardinal <hi>Granvil</hi>'s Breeches had lost the <hi>Guleta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heliodorus,</hi> was so captivated and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with his <hi>Aethyopian,</hi> or amorous History of <hi>Cariclea,</hi> which was to be called in by reason of some loose pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages therein, or he to lose his Bishop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick; that the mitred Gentleman made choice of the latter, rather lose his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, than his pleasure and wanton hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Octavian</hi> of St. <hi>Gelais,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Angou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisme</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> (yet the worthy Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator of <hi>Ovid de arte amandi</hi>) was so Poetically waggish, that he would lay a Wager, he could answer any one <hi>Extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore,</hi> should speak to him in Rythme. Done and done, Cock-pit Law; the Wager is agreed upon and laid, and these three Verses were repeated to him, whil'st he was dandling his breaden God.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>L'autre jour venant de l'Escole,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ie trouvai la Dame Nicole,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Laquelle étoit de verd vestue.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:199119:55"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Coming from School the other Day,</l>
                     <l>I met with bonny Bess by th' Way.</l>
                     <l>Cloathed all in green.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>To which he readily, replied without interruption to his devout Missification.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ostez moy du col cest 'estole,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et si bien tost je ne l'accole,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I'auray la gageure perdu.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Some one take off my Stole, I pray,</l>
                     <l>And if I kiss her not straightway,</l>
                     <l>I'll lose the Wager clean.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>A pretty amorous and kissative Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late indeed? This can be no less than <hi>Osculum Charitatis,</hi> let what Female so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever receive it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their Cruelty, Massacres, Murthers, Coveteousness, Ignorance.</head>
               <p>NOr have we done with Cardinal <hi>Granvil;</hi> for tho we concluded the last, we must begin this Chapter with
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:199119:56"/>him. He was more than suspected to be an Atheist, very much addicted to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments, Sorcery and Poysoning; and he made an Essay of this his black Art on the wise and virtuous <hi>Maximilian</hi> the second, King of the <hi>Romans;</hi> yet this walking Monument of Vices was lookt upon by the Pope and King of <hi>Spain</hi> to be a very fit Instrument in setling the holy Inquisition in the <hi>Netherlands;</hi> a proper Agent, sufficiently qualified with Cruelty for that bloody Employment he was to excute.</p>
               <p>This bloody Inquisition had no Cloak to shrowd it's Tyranny, but pious fraud covered with Robes of Sanctity, erected in several Parts of <hi>Europe</hi> (but we will only mention that of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> wherein the Cardinal was so much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd) was confirmed and ratified by Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth. This bloody <hi>Granvil,</hi> a Sanguine Cardinal, must be the good Man appointed to settle this horrid Inquisition, who, with the assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of that Monster the Duke <hi>d'Alva,</hi> puts all in a Flame and Combustion; and to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:199119:56"/>enumerate the Troubles, Miseries, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties, Massacres, Murthers, Barbarismes, and Devastations both of that People and Country, is a Task beyond my Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and too sanguinary for a Man of my Constitution: only in short, these In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisitors did imprison and execute all Protestants with the most exquisite and incredible Tortures; confiscate their Goods, and the Proprietors were ruin'd, expell'd, imprison'd, chain'd, fetter'd, burned, hanged, beheaded, broken on Wheeles, hanged alive by the Feet; nay, these are but Infant-Cruelties, in the very Cradle, compar'd to the Wrack, the Trough of Water, Pulley: Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risms far exceeding the Bull of <hi>Phalaris, Regulus</hi> his nailed Barrel, or the Tortures of the most bloody and arbitrary Tyrants among Infidels; Cruelties that would melt a Rock, and so inhuman, that it is a Crime to think on them without the Tribute of a Tear: nothing was to be seen throughout this miserable Country but Wheels, Gibbets, Stakes, Wracks, and wretched Objects of Pity; nothing to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:199119:57"/>be heard but the cries of poor <hi>Orphans</hi> and Widows for their Parents and Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, the Sons living a deplorable life in Woods, the Daughters and Virgins ravished and brutishly used, beyond all Modesty; insomuch that Cruelty in a Human shape could not have been more outragious and destructive, then these modern <hi>Pharaohs.</hi> The Duke <hi>d'Alva,</hi> that Spunge of <hi>Belgian</hi> blood, boasted, that in six years he had dispatch't to the other World by Course of Justice, at least 18000 <hi>Belgians,</hi> and yet the President of his Council said, that he quite spoiled the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlanders</hi> with too much Clemency and Mercy; so that it might very well be said of him, as it was once of the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Caligula;</hi> that he never spared Man in his Rage. Nobility, Honor, Merit, Chastity, nor any Virtue, could priviledge the Possessors from the Wrack, Pulley, Gibbet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the usual Attendants of these distressed Souls, and constantly waited on their Hearses. They were so rigorously us'd by these Lords Inquisitors, that their very Thoughts must be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prest
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:199119:57"/>and stifled for fear of Discovery; (so that the Proverb fail'd here, Thoughts were not free) for fear of the same mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune of the Knight at <hi>Rome,</hi> who was executed for putting a Dream into Words; Nay, the Torments of some were warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to all; witness the timorous temper of <hi>Sevilian,</hi> who had a fruitful Pear-tree growing in his Garden, and the Inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors requested some of that Fruit; but he for fear of displeasing them, pluckt up the very Tree it self by the Roots, and freely bestow'd it on them, Fruit and Tree and all. I will conclude this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph, with the saying of an <hi>English</hi> Knight, upon another occasion; if all Cruelties were lost, they might be found in this Inquisition; and yet this was set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled, promoted, and principally managed by the Religious Clergy-man, Cardinal <hi>Granvil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Reign of <hi>Otho</hi> the Emperour, <hi>Hatto</hi> Bishop of <hi>Mentz</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> was so pitiful to the Poor, that in a time of great Dearth and Want, he assembled a great Multitude of them together, put
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:199119:58"/>them in a Barn, and then set it on fire and burnt them; justifying his inhuman Action, with as inhuman and unepisco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal an Expression, That they differed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all from Rats, and Vermin that devoured the Corn, and consequently were good for nothing. But, he that sits above all, and sees all, sent such Troops of Rats to execute his Vengeance, that they eat him up alive; though he thought to defend himself from their assaults, by climbing up his lofty Tower, but they pursued him thither, and never left hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him from Place to Place, till they had dispatcht and devour'd him; and this Place is called the Rats Tower to this very day.</p>
               <p>And yet (so obdurate are some Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in their Cruelty) notwithstanding this severe Judgment executed upon the former Miter'd Offender; <hi>Herebert,</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of <hi>Cologne,</hi> was so unhappy, as to be related to a Brother, Heir of the like Cruelty to the Poor, in the like Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity.</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:199119:58"/>
               <p> The Cardinal of St. <hi>Eustace,</hi> poyson<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 5th, who might rather be said to usurp the Papal Throne, then to be fairly made choice of, and elected to it, and adopted to himself the name of <hi>John</hi> the 23th.</p>
               <p>The cruel Prelate of <hi>Verdan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. Comines.</note> was the first that ever shewed King <hi>Lewis</hi> the 11th, the Invention of Iron Cages; and for a reward of his Mitred Cruelty, was justly mewed up in one of them, to make the first Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Invention, and confin'd like a bloody Bird of prey, to that Cage for 14 years together.</p>
               <p>As to their Avarice, and Covetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; <hi>Pontanus</hi> in his Book of Liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, tells you, that one Cardinal <hi>Angelot,</hi> was such a close-fisted griping Miser, that he would creep privately by night into his own Stable, and steal away the allowance of Hay from the poor Horses; which he so constantly us'd, that his resolute, and bold Horseler took heart of Grace, and bang'd him well-favourdly for his pains.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:199119:59"/>
               <p> It is reported, that when a covetous Prelate begg'd a fat Benefice of <hi>Lewis</hi> the 12th, King of <hi>France,</hi> (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Pluralities he already en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd) he made him this answer, <hi>Tot da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo tibi, quod Diabolus portabit omnia,</hi> I shall give thee so long, that the Devil will carry all away at last.</p>
               <p>As to the leud Lives, Fraud and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veteousness, of the Popish Clergy; there is a standing Monument thereof in the stone walls of the Library at <hi>Fulda,</hi> which remains still to their Reproch, <hi>viz.</hi> the Picture of a Wolf with a shaven Crown, a Monk's Cowle, leaning on a Staff, and preaching to a company of Geese, and this is his Doctrin; <hi>Testis est mihi Deus quam cupiam vos omnes in vis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceribus meis;</hi> and another of a Cat, with a Miter on her Head, and a Crosier in her Paw, instructing the Mice; to whom one of the most apprehensive of those diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Animals, as nimble with her tongue, as her feet said; <hi>Charius est mihi ut mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riar Paganus, quam sub vestra manu fiam
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:199119:59"/>Christianus;</hi> but crafty Mrs. <hi>Evans</hi> sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly replies,
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quod fueram non sum Frater, caput aspice tonsum.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I am not what I was of late,</l>
                     <l>Brother, behold my shaven Pate. But she rejoyns,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cor tibi restat idem, vix tibi praesto fidem.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thy heart's the same as formerly;</l>
                     <l>Therefore I dare not credit thee.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>These Pictures are above 200 years old, and do notably discover the temper of the Prelacy, and are not a whit the worse, because <hi>Wicelius</hi> calls them <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theranissimas,</hi> but the better.</p>
               <p>As to their Pride, Stupidity and block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish Ignorance; It is recorded in History, of the Cardinal of <hi>Avignon,</hi> that when the <hi>French</hi> King saw the Grandeur, State, and Pomp of the Popes Court, and the Haughtiness and Pride of his Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals; he ask't him whether the <hi>Apostles</hi> were ever lacquey'd with such a Train at their heels, or attended by
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:199119:60"/>such a numerous Retinue? To whom he answer'd, No surely Sir. But you must un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that they were <hi>Apostles,</hi> when Kings were Shepheards, that's the reason.</p>
               <p>Arch-bishop <hi>Parker,</hi> in his <hi>Antiq. Britan.</hi> saith, that a <hi>French</hi> Bishop, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to take his Oath before the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> met with the word <hi>Metropoliticae,</hi> which he could by no means Pronounce, so ignorant he was, and therefore past it over with this bald expression in <hi>French, Soit pour dit,</hi> Let it be so said or spoken; so be it.</p>
               <p>He was a wise Bishop indeed, (as wise as the Fellow that put out the Candle, that the Fleas might not see to bite and sting him with their <hi>proboscis,</hi>) who commenced a Suit with his Canons, which prov'd very dilatory, but he at last overthrew them, and took order in his life time, that his Tomb should not lye along in the Church as others do, but stand upright, for fear that after his death they should piss upon his Body by way of revenge. A pretty Pastor, who took more care of his Body while
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:199119:60"/>living, than of the state of his Soul after death.</p>
               <p>Not many Years ago, a President of the high Court of Parliament, was so just and modest as to beg the favour of a Night's Lodging with a Lady of Quality and Honour, upon which Terms he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised her audience, the Lady having at that time a Cause depending before him: his Name I will conceal, but withall give you this notice of him, that it was the same Person, who not not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being made an <hi>Abbot,</hi> wrote a severe Book against the <hi>Lutherans</hi> (which he dedicated to the Pope) in so harsh and uncouth a Stile, that his Holiness was resolv'd to make Cul-paper of it; for go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one day to the Close-Stool (to shew as <hi>Platina</hi> says, that he is subject to the Necessities and Infirmities of Nature as well as other Persons) to ease himself, brought a Disease upon himself by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king cleanly use of a Leaf of it; for it did so chafe and gall his Apostolick Seat, that he lost a great deal of Leather, and was as sore in the Fundament as he could
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:199119:61"/>have been in the Feet, had his Devotion put him upon the Trott in a Pilgrimage to <hi>Jerusalem.</hi> See the dire Effects of crabbed Latin; 'tis ten times worse than the Piles, Hemorrhoids or <hi>Fistula in ano;</hi> but I'll warrant you this was such a warning to him, that his Holiness, of his own accord, and for his own good, without the Advice of a Physician, did forbear ever after the use of such excori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating Abstersives.</p>
               <p>This Question was once propos'd in a Councel, <hi>An sint Episcopi immediate à Christo, an mediate à Pontifice?</hi> A Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Bishop moved with it, made this learned and <hi>Christian</hi> reply, <hi>Parcat mihi Dominus Christus, non sum ab ipso.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another of their Reverend Doctors, being quite baffled and beat off of the Stage with downright Scripture, plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this as an excuse, <hi>Ego non sum Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logus, Ego sum Canonicus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One of these <hi>Reverendissimi,</hi> was not at all asham'd to declare openly his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, that such young Fellows and Boys should now a days quote the new
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:199119:61"/>Testament, <hi>per diem,</hi> whereas he did solemnly and truly profess, that he was fifty years of Age and upward before he was so wise as to understand what the New Testament meant.</p>
               <p>But here we will bid adieu to these <hi>Illustrissimos,</hi> and pass from the Cardinal's red-Hat, to the Jesuits black-Cap; which I fear will prove more mischievous.</p>
               <p>Take but a view of some of their Pranks, and you'l find them as expert and knowing in the exquisite Methods of crafty and circumventing Wickedness, as any of the Popes or preceeding Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals.</p>
               <p>As to the name of Jesuit, it breaths nothing but health and prosperity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deriv'd from Jesus; but as to the nature of the Persons, nothing but death and damnation; and for their presumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in assuming to themselves this name, they were very much maligned, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at first, and that was the reason they called themselves afterwards <hi>Socios Jesu,</hi> the Companions of Jesus. Now in the sacred Writ, if you strictly examine it
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:199119:62"/>throughout, you will find only one, and that a goodly one, that was call'd Christ's Companion, <hi>viz. Judas:</hi> so much for their name. They have also a Nick-name, which they will carry to their Graves. When they first negotiated for footing in <hi>Paris,</hi> they demanded what they were, whether Seculars or Regulars; and they made answer, <hi>Tales Quales,</hi> Such and Such; a Nick-name, which they will ne're be able to claw off, for they are upbraid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it to this very day.</p>
               <p>The Glorious Patron of these Popish <hi>Janizaries,</hi> was an infirm <hi>Enthusiastick Spanish</hi> Souldier, and Cripple; and they, in imitation of him, their first founder, do hault lamely ever since; his name was <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> who being a Souldier in those times when <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Arra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi> invaded the Kingdom of <hi>Navarr,</hi> and opposed King <hi>John de Albret,</hi> whom the Pope had excommunicated, because he supplied the King with Succours; At this very time was this <hi>Loyola</hi> a Soldier at <hi>Pampelona,</hi> where he was maimed; it being then besieg'd by the King: this
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:199119:62"/>Patron of that Holy Order resolv'd to erect a Society of Jesuits, which should be able from that time forward to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and uphold the Usurpations of his Holy Master, and to promote the Power of the unerring Prelate of <hi>Rome;</hi> which they do infinitely prefer beyond the Life, Honour, and Good of Kings: to which purpose these Fauters of the Popes Power have a peculiar Vow, and take an Oath of blind Obedience a fourth Vow un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to other Orders, whereby they move Subjects against their Sovereigns, and stirr them up to Rebellion against their Lawful Princes.</p>
               <p>Let us begin with their Blasphemies both in Expressions and Opinions; and you shall find them very bold as to these Particulars.</p>
               <p>These are they that infected <hi>Ravilliac,</hi> that monstrous Assassine, with these and the like Blasphemies, That to make War against the Pope was to make War against God; that God is the Pope and the Pope is God. O horrid! <hi>Lucianisme</hi> is modest
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:199119:63"/>to such <hi>Christianisme</hi> comparatively. These are the Persons who blasphemously substi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute another God on Earth besides our Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father in Heaven, whom they stile most Holy Father, and separate Jesus Christ from his Body and Spouse, the Holy Church, creating him a Vicar-General or Vice-gerent in all his Kingdoms: <hi>etiam Christo secluso.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bel. l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Pontif c.</hi> 9.</note> What shall we say of such a pack of Saints as these. The <hi>Saracens</hi> had an antient Law, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever should blaspheme the name of Christ, or the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> should be starved to death between two Boards.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Galeacius,</hi> a Duke, hanged a Man only for murmuring aginst him. And the Duke of <hi>Mantua</hi> put another to death for the like Offence; and must Blasphemy against the Almighty go unpunish'd in such pretended Sanctimonious <hi>Religiosi</hi> as these <hi>Jesuits</hi> seem to be? But we'll leave the punishment of this Crime to that Lord whose Morto is, <hi>Revenge is mine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Father <hi>Garnett</hi> the <hi>Jesuit,</hi> one of the Gun-powder-Plot, had this Question put to him by the Earl of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> Whether
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:199119:63"/>if any one should confess to him in the Morning that he intended to murther the King next Evening, he was bound in Conscience to reveal it? To whom he answered in the Negative: and <hi>Binetus,</hi> another of the Tribe, confirms this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, in these words to <hi>Casaubon; Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stare Reges omnes perire, quam si vel semel Confessionis Sigillum violaretur; Regem enim ait humani, Juris Imperium esse, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessionem Juris divini.</hi> Nay farther, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jesuit</hi> in <hi>France</hi> was so audacious as to affirm openly; <hi>Si Dominus noster Jesus Christus in Terris versaretur morti obnoxius, et aliquis sibi in Confessione di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xisse velle se illum occidere, priusquam Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessionem revelaret passurum se, ut Christus occidatur;</hi> that is, If our Lord Jesus Christ were upon Earth, Mortal, and a Person should Confess to him, that he would kill him; he would rather suffer our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to be murthered than reveal his Confession.</p>
               <p>Nor are they less practised in horrid Murthers than Blasphemies.</p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:199119:64"/>
               <p>'Twas a young stripling of this Pious Order, that stabbed <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth in the Mouth with his Parricide Knife, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending his Murther, tho it only proved the loss of a Tooth; which moved the good King to no other return, than this pleasant Repartie. <hi>Falloit il que les Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suistes fussent convanicus par ma bouche.</hi> Must the <hi>Jesuits</hi> be confuted by my own Mouth? Hereupon they were command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to depart the Kingdom by a certain Day, and a new Stone-Gallows erected before the Palace Gate for the Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Offender; (tho the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Decree against this wicked Act was made null at <hi>Rome,</hi>) and afterwards the <hi>Pusillanimous</hi> Prince removed it out of fear; which made one descant wittily upon this timorous Action of the King's, in this <hi>French Quatrain.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sire si vous voulez du tout a l'advenir,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>De l' Assassin Chastel oster le souvenir,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ostant la Pyramide &amp; l' Arrest qui le tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qu'on vous remette donc une dent dans la bouche.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:199119:64"/>
                  <l>Great Sir if you will have succeeding times,</l>
                  <l>Ignorant of th' Assassine <hi>Chastl</hi>'s Crimes;</l>
                  <l>Waving th' Arrest and Gibbet, Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign dread,</l>
                  <l>Let him another Tooth set in your Head.</l>
               </q>
               <p>But this was only a Prologue to the ensuing Tragedy acted by <hi>Francis Ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liac,</hi> born at <hi>Angoulesme</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> who, after he had attempted four several times to kill the King, tho still happily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, began that day with Confession, and seeming Devotion, whereon he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrated that horrid Murther, (which was on Friday the 14th of <hi>May, An.</hi> 1610.) and employed the remaining part to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Kings Coach, to find out a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient opportunity, which he met with at last, to the great damage and irrepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable loss of that Kingdom; which he accomplisht at last with a Stilletto, and two Stabs in the side, near the Church of St. <hi>Innocents,</hi> at the end of the Street of <hi>Ferronnerie,</hi> the King being in his <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rosse,</hi> that was put to the stand by the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:199119:65"/>stoppage of a Coach and Cart; which he perceiving, being then in a shop hard by, waiting the good hour, as he thought, came out and killed the King, and suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for it upon a Scaffold, in the usual place of Execution; where he died with most exquisite and deserved Torments. All which was done by the Instigation of this wicked and cruel Society. They perswaded this Monster, that the King intended to make War against the Pope, and that to make War against him, was a <hi>Theomachy,</hi> or open War with the Deity; and there was found about him a Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter with a Heart of Cotton hung about his Neck, which he shewed the <hi>Jesuit D' Aubinie,</hi> who confessed him and the Knife, whereon was ingraven a Heart and a Cross; and that which was one oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of this barbarous Fact, was, That these Persons of the Popes Party had published throughout the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that whosoever should serve <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Fourth in these Wars, tho he was their Lawful and undoubted King, could not avoid damnation.</p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:199119:65"/>
               <p> The Gun-powder Plot was another <hi>Jesuitical</hi> Contrivance. The Provincial, Father <hi>Garnet,</hi> was privy to it in its ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry infancy, so were others of that Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as <hi>Baldwin, Hammond, Tesmund</hi> and <hi>Gerard,</hi> who were all particularly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Conspirators in their Confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. A Fact of that dreadful Consequence, had it taken effect, and so heinous in it self, that <hi>Garnet</hi> the <hi>Jesuite</hi> said himself before Doctor <hi>Overal</hi> and others, <hi>That he would give all the world, were it at his disposal, to clear his Conscience or Name from that hateful Treason.</hi> Yet when it did miscarry, many of that Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had a Religious Veneration for these Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious Wretches who were deeply en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in it. What a Coil was there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the feigned Miracle of <hi>Garnet</hi>'s Structure! and his Picture, as well as <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard</hi>'s, was to be seen at <hi>la Fleche,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Places among the Martyrs of that Society. In the Town of <hi>Dole</hi> towards <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the <hi>Jesuits</hi> have a great House given them, called <hi>L'arc,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth gave them <hi>la Fleche,</hi> upon the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:199119:66"/>
                  <hi>Loire,</hi> two stately Covents, among many other Houses for change, which they have, (see the gratitude of these Villains, to be the Death of their princely Patron) tho this latter may be called a Quiver, containing 8000 poysoned Shafts of all si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes; hereupon their <hi>Ferrier</hi> played up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them this merry Distich;
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Arcum Dola dedit, dedit his la Flecha Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gittam;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sed quis funem illis quem meruere dabit?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>La Fleche</hi> th' Arrow, <hi>Dole</hi> gave them the Bow,</l>
                     <l>But who'll on them the deserv'd Rope bestow?</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, his Holiness himself, Pope <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the 8th, who first promoted this Treason by his Breves, did sufficiently testifie his good Will towards them, by making the <hi>Jesuit Tesmund</hi> Penetentiary at St. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> after the discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrid Plot.</p>
               <p>And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Divinity is of as deep a Searlet Dye a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their sanguinary and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:199119:66"/>bloody Actions; for they give free liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and permisson to any Person to kill another, from whom he fears any Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice or Damage, either in Reputation or Estate, though he is assured he will be damned; this is <hi>Molina's</hi> Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, who averrs,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Molina de Just. commutat. tr.</hi> 3. <hi>d.</hi> 13. <hi>n.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 762.</note> that this Circumstance ought not to be pleaded in Bar of the Action, to hinder him from the Murther; and that there is no Law of Justice or Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it self, which obligeth us to spare the eternal Life of the Soul any more than that of the Body.</p>
               <p>These are Tenets fit to be drawn out in blood, worse than those of <hi>Draco</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Legislator. As for their Doctrine of mental Reservation, it is very remarkable.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sanchez. Opin. Moral. Par.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>n.</hi> 13.</note>
                  <hi>Sanchez</hi> maintains, that a Man may swear he hath not done a thing which is really done by him, by understanding within himself, that he did it not on such or such a Day, or before he was born, or by making Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections on some other Circumstances of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:199119:67"/>the like nature; and so the words spoken by him shall have a different meaning, and imply nosuch thing as is said. This is of general use, and great convenience upon many emergent Occasions; and is ever justifiable when a Man's Health, Honour, or Estate, lyes at stake and may be injured;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Filintius Tract.</hi> 25. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>n.</hi> 331.</note> Nay, <hi>Filintius,</hi> to confirm this, says the Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on regulates, and squares the the Action; and for Encouragement of those who have wicked craft enough to furnish them with particular Reservations, he alledgeth, That to avoid Lying no more is required, than to say simply, they have not done that which in truth they have, provided they have a general In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to stamp the sence upon their Discourse, which a Prudent and Discreet Person would do. And indeed these their Equivocations did insert, that Clause in the Oath of Supremacy among us here in <hi>England, Without mental Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this doubtless was the Reason that moved one to bestow on them that
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:199119:67"/>so much merited Title, calling them <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinnatores mendaces,</hi> the Polishers of Lyes, their Tongues being whetted and sharp'ned to that purpose.</p>
               <p>These are the Croaking Frogs, the Amphibious Insects that live both by Land and Water, in Church and State; not a Kings Privy Council, not a Ladies Chamber, not a Lord's Closet, not a House or Cottage, nay, not so much as a Soul, but is daily haunted by these Spectres and evil Spirits; not a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man or Lady can cross the Seas, but his, or her name is landed before hand in the <hi>Jesuits</hi> Register. It was not without cause, that their <hi>Mecaenas</hi> and Patron, <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> the second, King of <hi>Spain,</hi> baptized them, <hi>Clerigos Negotiadores,</hi> Negotiating or Trafficking, Trading Clergy-Men; and that <hi>Marcus Antonius Columna,</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the Navy belonging to <hi>Pius</hi> the fifth, in the famous Battel of <hi>Lepanto,</hi> and Viceroy of <hi>Sicily,</hi> did tell <hi>Don Alonso,</hi> (a noted <hi>Jesuit,</hi> who endeavoured to be of the Council of his Conscience) very plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and roundly, as well as truly, <hi>Voi altri
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:199119:68"/>Padri di Giesu havete la mente al Cielo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> le mani al Mondo, l'anima al Diavolo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> You <hi>Jesuitical</hi> Fathers have your thoughts seemingly in Heaven, your hands on the Wealth and Riches of the World, and your Souls with the Devil. And this their griping for worldly gain, and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the rest of the Clergy (one of the three Particulars before mentioned) was the reason that a Reverend Divine did say, tho the great <hi>Pan</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> had committed the greatest part, if not all his spotted-Sheep to the Pastoral charge of Arch-Bishops, Bishops <hi>&amp;c.—Pan curat oves ovium{que} magistros;</hi> yet they yield them little or no profit, because they are sheared to their hands, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by the <hi>Jesuits,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vindiciae Sacrae Satyr. M. S.</note> whom <hi>Reverardentius</hi> aptly termeth in this respect, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>quites aurei Velleris,</hi> Knights of the Golden Fleece. And for this cause a Reverend Divine says, that they want no maintenance: what by traducing our Nation abroad, and feducing our People at home, their Bones are full of marrow, and their Eyes
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:199119:68"/>swell with fatness; for a Country Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son cannot make so much of a whole years Harvest as one <hi>Jesuit</hi> can get by an hours single Confession.</p>
               <p>When two <hi>Jesuits</hi> presented their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to Duke <hi>Cezarini,</hi> and made a Complaint to him, that Father <hi>Oliva</hi> their General, had been wrought upon by the insinuating Perswasions of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the seventh, to part with some of their Lands, for the sum of 100000 Crowns, (so covetous they were as by their good will to part with nothing that once came into their Clutches,) he gave them this witty and undeniable answer, Those men who believe the Popes Infallibility, as you do, must by no means complain against him, for if he be Infallible he can do no wrong, nor be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of an irregular or injurious Action.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>A Popish Writer of our Nation, (as he himself thought) not unlearned,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bishop</hi> Hall <hi>in his Quo Vadis, as he hath the story out of Robert Pointz in his Preface to the Testimony of the real Presence.</hi>
                     </note> complaining of the Abstinence of us He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, despairs of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing, because he found
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:199119:69"/>it to be long ago fore-prophecied of us, in the second Book of <hi>Chronicles, c.</hi> 24. <hi>At illi Protestantes audire noluerunt;</hi> it is well (saith he) that the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stauts were yet heard of in the old Testam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t, as well as the <hi>Jesuits,</hi> whose name one of their own found out by good hap,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Secar. in Josua l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 19. <hi>&amp; Gresser contra</hi> Lernaeum <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note>
                     <hi>Numbers</hi> 26. <hi>ver.</hi> 24. like as <hi>Erasmus</hi> found <hi>Fryars</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s time <hi>inter falsos Fratres.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Father <hi>Hayndius,</hi> a <hi>Jesuit</hi> of thirty three years standing, found this not to be the least of fifty two Complaints which he made against his own Society, to their General <hi>Aquaviva;</hi> that his Fellows did not blush to blemish their Order, and stain their Honour by cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of Miracles, and cheating the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant into a belief of them. What fardles of Lies do they impose upon the Vulgar, concerning their <hi>Indian</hi> Wonders? Nay, Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is not ashamed to appear as their Voucher, and dares maintain their Frauds and Cozenages, affirming, that his Brother <hi>Xavier</hi> had
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:199119:69"/>not only cured the Deaf, Lame, and Blind, but also raised the Dead, (it seems he was so intent upon his new Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, that he quite forgot his old Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophy, <hi>A privatione ad habitum non da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur regressus</hi>) while his Fellow <hi>Acosta,</hi> who continued many years in those Parts, pulls him by the sleeve, and is down-right with him, whispering so loud in his Ear that all the World may hear him,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acosta. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 12. <hi>de salut. Indic.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Prodigia nulla produci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ne{que} vero est opus. Africk</hi> is at the best but barren of Novelties, if compared to <hi>Rome;</hi> and yet the World of Protestants must be branded with Incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity, if they will not be gull'd by their pious Frauds; but let them remember, if they are at leisure, that <hi>simulata Sanctitas est duplex Iniquitas;</hi> Counterfeit Sanctity is double Iniquity, and one sin is made two, when once defended; Nay, it is more than feared, that they will not want Diabolical Delusions, and Hellish Incan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, rather than lose a Proselite; which are so gross, and frequently put in practice among them, that it hath puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:199119:70"/>the best Casuists to make a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between their Magick and that which is Diabolical. Hence it is that some of our weak People have been frightned out of the World upon their Death-Beds, and scared into the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks. Take this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table instance, among many other, from a famous Divine in <hi>France,</hi> second to none for Learning and Fidelity, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated it with his own mouth, and his own certain Knowledge and Experience. A Gentleman of the Religion, whose Wife was one of the Popish Frie, sends for his own Pastor to discourse with him, being upon his last bed of Sickness, and ready to depart; she likewise ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points a <hi>Jesuit</hi> to be there, who appears accordingly, and both meet at the Bed's<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side; both plead for their own different Religion, and perswade the Man to come over to their Party, but after two hours smart Disputation at the Bar, before these Judges, the Gentleman was very well satisfied with the Religion that he had hitherto embraced, and his Consort also,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:199119:70"/>by the prevalence of the Protestants Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, began to incline to his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The <hi>Jesuit</hi> finding himself foil'd, went away discontented, but returns a few hours after, when the storm was blown over, and the Coast clear, desiring a private Conference with the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, which was granted; and her Garden was the Scene appointed for the ensuing Tragedy, where they took a turn or two together, and the <hi>Jesuit</hi> very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly expostulated with her, and used all the perswasive and inclining Arguments imaginable, to keep her from that sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed and falsely termed Defection from the Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> the change of Religion; and in the close of all his Discourse, did very much importune her to do him that signal Favour, as to accept of a little Box, (like <hi>Pandor'as,</hi> as it fell out) which he then and there presented to her, and to wear it constantly about her for his sake; which she received as innocent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as courteously, little dreaming of the ensuing mischief that after befell her; for she no sooner had followed his directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:199119:71"/>on, but she fell into so great and abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute a Detestation of her Husband, that she could never endure the sight of him afterwards; and within two days died in this miserable condition: an Act fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the sharp Sword of revenging Justice, than the Pen of an Historian.</p>
               <p>They are a People disesteemed and ill thought of in most Places where-ever they get footing, for their Impieties, and and wicked Practices. They have been banisht <hi>France, Hungary, Germany, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> nay, the <hi>Grand Turk,</hi> upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of their Vileness by Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi>'s Ambassador, exiled them out of <hi>Pera,</hi> near <hi>Constantinople.</hi> They are hated by the common People in <hi>Spain,</hi> tho the Subjects of the most Catholick King, as appears by this Libel.
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Los mandamientes de los Teatinos,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mas humanos son que Divinos.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Precepts of the <hi>Jesuits Teatine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are much more Humane than Divine.</l>
                  </q> And after the enumeration of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calogue or ten Commandments, as to
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:199119:71"/>grow Rich, feed well, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it concludes thus;
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Estos diez mandamièntes se encierrian en das,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To do para mi, y nada para vos.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>These ten are compris'd in two,</l>
                     <l>All for me, and nothing for you.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I did not promise you, as I remember, to give you an Essay of <hi>Jesuitical</hi> Piquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but yet if you please, take this as an Argument of their pregnant Wit, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by the deceased Author of the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly State;</hi> who speaking of Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> stiles her deservedly,
<q>the Paragon of spotless Chastity, whatever some Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Priests (who count all Virginity hid under a <hi>Nun</hi>'s Veile,) have feigned to the contrary. He proceeds farther, and says, One <hi>Jesuit</hi> made this false <hi>Anagram</hi> on her, <hi>Edmund Campian</hi> by name, <hi>Elizabeth, Jezabel,</hi> false both in matter and manner; for allow it the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batement of the H (as all <hi>Anagrams</hi> must Sue in <hi>Chancery</hi> for moderate fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour) which proved tho no Letter,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:199119:72"/>a guttural aspiration to the Composer, yet was it both unequal and ominous that T, a solid Letter, should be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; the Presage of the Gallows, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Anagrammatist</hi> was afterwards justly executed.</q> When Flies grow once so blind as to play with the Candle, they either sindge their wings, or burn themselves, and when ill-boading Ravens dare be so haughty and proud, as to fly at the Eagle, the King of Birds, may they all have the same fate as the Brother of this <hi>Jesuitical</hi> breed before mentioned.</p>
               <p>Now let us anatomize and dissect the Members of this Catholick, and Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal Head of the Church, and see how they stand affected, whether they are fit for Physick or Amputation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their Priests, Friars, Nuns, and Laymen.</head>
               <p>WE will still continue our Method, and begin with the Blasphemies, Oaths, and Execrations, of the inferiour
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:199119:72"/>Clergy, the Monks and Friars, those Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibals of the Crucifix.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Italy</hi> abounds in Blasphemies more than any other Country, and therein the Clergy are far better Proficients than the Laity, or else, <hi>He swears like an Abbot,</hi> would not be Proverbial. Nor do I think as it is, that is to be matcht that was belch'd out by a Priest at <hi>Rome, Al dispetto di quel Can che pendeva nella croce.</hi> I forbear the <hi>English</hi> of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause 'tis so horrid an Expression; and what should move him to this think you? Nothing, as he confess'd, but that his Strumpet had played him a slippery Trick; as if there were no way to be even with his Whore, but to revile his God.</p>
               <p>A ghostly Father Preaching at <hi>Tours</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> said, These Hugonots are so impudently wicked, as to renounce the Pope, and his Authority; but I'll be bold to tell you, that if Christ and the Pope were both here upon Earth, and the one should command me to do a
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:199119:73"/>Thing, and the other forbid me, I would sooner obey the Pope than Christ.</p>
               <p>An <hi>Italian</hi> Preacher broacht this blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Doctrine in the Pulpit before a great Auditory; that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> would have crucified our Saviour, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than he should go without Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixion; strengthning his blasphemous Discourse with this strange Allegation, that it did proceed from the longing desire that his blessed Mother had to hasten the Salvation of Mankind.</p>
               <p>There is another story related by the same Priest, much of the same nature; That the Apostles drew up Articles of Impeachment against Christ, and present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to his Mother, complaining that he was not as good as his word in send<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Holy Ghost upon them, and that there was a Dissention between the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Holy Ghost, who feared to descend from Heaven, and come into the World, lest he should have the same course Entertainment as our Saviour had from the murthering <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:199119:73"/>
               <p> Another Priest, by relating the Agony that our Saviour endured at his painful and shameful Death on the Cross, drew Rivulets of Tears from the Eyes of his compassionate Auditory, but he dried up all their Sorrow with this point of Consolation, Weep not my Beloved, for perhaps it is not true.</p>
               <p>But the Devil himself with all his Hellish Assistance could never invent such Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies as are found in the Book of Conformities, printed at <hi>Milain</hi> by <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard Pontice, Anno</hi> 1510. As that Christ changed Water into Wine but once, St. <hi>Francis</hi> thrice, Christ felt the Pain of his Wounds but a small time, St. <hi>Francis</hi> two whole Years compleat. As for Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, Christ did nothing comparatively to St. <hi>Francis:</hi> for he cured a 1000 Blind, and as many Lame, both Beasts and Men; cast out 1000 Daemoniacks, and raised above 1000 from the Dead. <hi>Gen. chap.</hi> 2. <hi>Let us make Man &amp;c.</hi> That is St. <hi>Francis:</hi> so that there is not so much as one Text in the Holy Writ, from the first of <hi>Genesis</hi> to the last of the <hi>Revelation,</hi>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:199119:74"/>which they have not wrested to magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Order of St. <hi>Francis;</hi> but I am tired with these Blasphemous <hi>Rodomonta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does,</hi> therefore I refer you to the Book it self, if you desire farther Satisfaction as to Particulars.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nilco Postel</hi> preaching at <hi>Paris,</hi> told them, in the very Face of the University, that an old Beldame (whom he called his Mother <hi>Joan</hi>) should save all Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as Christ did all Men; and as hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid as these Opinions were, he found many Catholicks that embraced them, all which he published in Print. This same Person was heard by several at the <hi>Rial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> in <hi>Venice</hi> to affirm, that if a Man would have a perfect Religion, these three Ingredients must necessarily go to its Composition, <hi>Christianism, Judaism,</hi> and <hi>Mahometism;</hi> and that upon serious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration there would appear to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent Doctrines in the <hi>Turkish Alcoran.</hi> If Treason against an earthly King is Capital, then doubtless <hi>à fortiori,</hi> Blasphemy against the King of Kings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves Death much more. In most Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:199119:74"/>of <hi>Italy</hi> these are but inconsiderable and poor Imprecations: <hi>Te venga 'l Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caro,</hi> and at <hi>Venice, Te venga la Ghiandussa, Te vengal mal di san Lazaro.</hi> I omit <hi>Puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na di Christo,</hi> and others of the like strain, as frequent as horrible; and the <hi>French</hi> have taken some of them upon trust, as <hi>Te viene le chancre,</hi> a Murrain on thee.</p>
               <p>In <hi>France</hi> they have certain Curses peculiar to their Language; <hi>Ad omnes Diabolos, ad triginta Mille Diabolos,</hi> used by Preachers in such barbarous Latin, taken from the French, who say, <hi>Je te donnea trente ou quarante mille charteès de Diables.</hi> Thirty or forty thousand Cart-loads of Devils take thee. And <hi>Menot</hi> the Preacher, <hi>fol.</hi> 129. falsly fathers this Curse on St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who hearing of one that had committed Fornication, said presently, I give him over to the Devils in Hell. He saith farther, <hi>fol.</hi> 47. of one of the two Harlots, that she would swear by her Faith. They have several ways of bequeathing themselves to the Devil (as if one were not enuf, or indeed too much) Body, Soul, and Guts; that no part may escape his Clutches, they make sure of all.</p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:199119:75"/>
               <p> Nor are the Laity so far exempted from these Vices, but that they have a spice of them; witness one of the Kings of <hi>Spain,</hi> who having had divers ill suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesses, swore he would be reveng'd on the Deity, and therefore commanded that none of his Subjects should adore God, believe in him, or mention his name for a certain time by him limited and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, without incurring a great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty, and his high displeasure.</p>
               <p>A certain Gamester losing at Cards, did curse and swear most desperately for his loss, and commanded his Servant to assist him in Curses, Oaths, and Execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, till his fortune should alter and he have better luck.</p>
               <p>A Secular person, as he was playing at Cards in the French Ambassadors House at <hi>Venice,</hi> belcht forth this Oath; <hi>Venga'l cancaro al Lupo.</hi> Why? What hurt in all this? Aye but his Villany was mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested afterwards, because he spake it by the Figure called <hi>Aposcopesis</hi> or <hi>Reticentia;</hi> instead of <hi>Venga'l cancaro al Lupo, che non mangiava Christo quando era Agnello,</hi>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:199119:75"/>calling Christ <hi>Agnello,</hi> in allusion to that of St. <hi>John; Ecce Agnus Dei qui tollit, &amp;c.</hi> As also the Blasphemy of the <hi>Italian,</hi> who frequently said, A Bots on the Ass that carried Christ to <hi>Jerusalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Italian</hi> Lord who had his Pass<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to the other World by a Pistol-shot, being desired to commend his Soul to God, beg'd of them to recommend him to the King, and withal to acquaint him, that he had lost a very good Servant, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; that he had often made it his business to believe in God, but could not; and withal was so Blasphemous as to add far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that God dealt very unjustly with Man in condemning him for a peice of an Apple; and that all he had learned by the New Testament was, that <hi>Joseph</hi> was a very idle Fellow, for not being jealous of his Wife; he being well strick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en in Years, and she so youthful.</p>
               <p>Nor must I omit that hellish Court-Curse, which is as common as Flies in <hi>Armenia,</hi> I would I might F— with such a Lady, or Gentlewoman upon pain of Damnation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:199119:76"/>
               <head>Of the Lechery, Whoredom, and Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the Clergy and Laiety.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITaly</hi> above all places abounds in these Vices, insomuch that it is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon saying;
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Jamais ni cheval ni homme</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>N'amenda, d'albera</hi> Rome.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nor Horse or Man e're return'd home</l>
                        <l>The better by the sight of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And Mr. <hi>Ascham,</hi> in his Preface to his Schoolmaster, did return thanks to God that he was but nine days in <hi>Italy,</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which time he saw in one City of <hi>Venice</hi> more liberty to sin, than in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> he ever heard of in as many Years.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Haywood,</hi> our old Epigrammatist, told Queen <hi>Mary</hi> very boldly, that her Clergy was very sawcy, and if they had not Wives, they would have their Lemans.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Richard</hi> the First being rounded in the Ear that he
<note place="margin">Daniel<hi>'s Hist.</hi> Rich. 1. <hi>in fine.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:199119:76"/>had three wicked Daughters, Pride, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetousness and Lechery, answered ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry briskly, Well be it so, if I have, I cannot better match them than with the Templers, Fathers and Friars. If a Priest be at any time found wantonly kissing a Woman, the usual excuse is, it was but to imprint a Blessing upon her Lips.</p>
               <p>It was once seriously debated, which was the best way to furnish <hi>Henry</hi> the Second with Mony. His Jester, seeing his Master at a great Loss, proposed this rational way, <hi>viz.</hi> that he should com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all the Monks Beds to be sold, and the Mony to be brought in to him. To which the King replied, where must the Monks then lye? O, said the Jester, with the Nuns; Alas! said the King, thou art mistaken; there are not near so many Nuns as Monks. And please your Majesty, said he, every Nun can lodge half a dozen Monks at the least, for her own share.</p>
               <p>'Tis a known Story of the two <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciscans</hi> who (because they are a Crew of beggarly Fellows,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Queen of</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varr<hi>'s Relations.</hi>
                  </note> never carry any mony about
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:199119:77"/>them) passed over a Ferry, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to pay their Passage, would have ravish'd the Ferry Woman in part of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, till they were enabled to Pay her her fare; a cunning new way to pay old Debts.</p>
               <p>Old <hi>Bromiar</hi> tells you, that a Ghost appeared to a Popish Priest, and said, there came daily so many Priests to Hell, as he thought verily there had been no more upon Earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poggius</hi> the <hi>Florentine</hi> reports, that <hi>Ausimerius,</hi> an Eremite of <hi>Padua,</hi> who lived in the reign of <hi>Francis</hi> the 7th, Duke of that City, had the reputation of a Pious and godly Man, till he was detected for corrupting and defiling many Women of Noble Extract, especially under the spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and Religious colour of sacred Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession; hereupon he was brought to Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al before the Duke, who ordered his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary to take a Catalogue of the names of the married Women that he had gallanted; and after a tedious enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many Persons of quality that fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented the Duke's Palace, the Secretary
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:199119:77"/>still pressed him to a farther Confession, whereat the poor Soul fetching a deep, but counterfeit Sigh, said, Why then Sir, since you are so urgent, pray set down your own Wife in the number, which sudden and unexpected Answer, did so surprise the Secretary with Astonishment, that the Pen fell out of his hand, and the Duke at the rehersal of the Story was almost resolved into Laughter: These tricks are so frequent among them, that 'tis commonly said as a Proverb; An <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> Friar in the Stews.</p>
               <p>In a Village near <hi>Coignac,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>This is in the Queen of</hi> Navarr<hi>'s Relations.</hi>
                  </note> called <hi>Cherves,</hi> a reputed Maid, Sister to the Curate of the Parish, who, because she was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a holy Virgin, spread a Rumour abroad among the credulous People, that she was a second Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and was impregnated by the holy Ghost: (O execrable Blasphemy!) But <hi>Charles</hi> Earl of <hi>Angoulesme,</hi> and Father to King <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> the First, hearing of it, did imagine there was some packing and gross villany in the Business, and took order for a more
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:199119:78"/>strict examination of this Wench, who was about 13 years of Age: The Court where she was summond to appear to make her defence, did adjure her, as well as her Brother, to reveal the Truth, upon her Salvation, and being sworn, she used this form of Affidavit; <hi>I take the Body of our Lord here present, upon my Salvation, before you my Masters, and you my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that never Man had any Carnal know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of me more than you;</hi> and so recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Eucharist. Having taken this Oath, as you have heard, they related the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of her Process to the Earl, who hearing it, thought on what they never dreamt of, that she had great reason to use that form of words, That never man touched her more than her Brother, and took it for granted, that he had raised her Belly; whereupon he commanded them to return and imprison the Curate, who upon his Commitment confessed the Fact; his Sister in few days lost her Tympany, and was delivered of a Child, and both of them were condemned to be Burnt, which Sentence was according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:199119:78"/>executed; and 'twas favourable enough too, considering the horrid Blasphemy and Perjury of the Criminals.</p>
               <p>A certain Curate, not far from <hi>Vienna</hi> in <hi>Daulphine,</hi> being taken in the Act with a notorious Strumpet (who had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten prostituted her self to his dissolute Embraces) behind the High Altar; and that on good <hi>Friday</hi> too, an aggravating Circumstance; the worthy Bishop of that Diocess, was to inflict a Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on him for this heinous Crime, and it was a merry one indeed, <hi>viz.</hi> to sing Mass for a certain time; but the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passionate Legate of <hi>Avignon,</hi> thought the Priest was too severely dealt with, and discharged him from that rigid Sentence, which encouraged the holy Man to play his tricks more frequently with the same Harlot, and in the same Place, than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly; thus to advance their sensual De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, these Clergy-men make Religion and Holiness, a Bawd to their own lasci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Wickedness. Methinks they should be more wary to observe the old Rule; <hi>Si non casté tamen cautè;</hi> and not affront the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:199119:79"/>Meridian Sun with their Noon days Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and this was the cause of that sporting reason that one gave why ghostly Fathers are called <hi>Beaux Peres,</hi> because, said he, they get Children at the High Altar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Abington,</hi> a lascivious Friar, could not be satisfied with the Use of three Concubines, but he must be ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stuous, (as if single Fornication were a small matter) for he had two Children by his own Sister; nay, some Friars and Monks have maintained twenty Whores at one time: a fine Crew indeed, able to fill a pretty <hi>Seraglio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Berenger,</hi> an <hi>Italian Marquess,</hi> enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a Chaplain in his House, as Persons of his Quality usually do, to perform the Duties of the Family, as to their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, for which he had a competency becoming one of his Coat, and to gratifie his Lord, lay with his Lady; and tho he was but a mere Dandiprat, as deformed in Body, as in mind, yet she notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Nobility of her Race, run the risco of so ignoble an Action; but he had his merited Compensation at last, which
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:199119:79"/>spoil'd his sport for the Future, for being discovered by the barking of an unlucky House Dog, he was taken, stript stark naked, and had his impetuous Nerve am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putated for the Offence. This hapned in the time of Pope <hi>Steven</hi> the Eighth, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the year 941.</p>
               <p>A Butcher of <hi>Strasbourg</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> by a strange accident lost his Wife, and not hearing the least syllable of her in a long time concluded she was Dead, and so she was to him in truth, tho not to the <hi>Franciscans,</hi> who kept her at Bed and Board; an Order so much extoll'd for their Sanctimony and Piety; but he found that there was a <hi>Franiscan</hi> Novice, who came daily to the Shambles accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with a ghostly Father, which the Butcher thought did so resemble his Wife, that he would often say, were he not perswaded that his Wife was dead, he should swear it were she. In fine, she proved to be what he thought her, his Wife indeed, which being discovered, and made known to the Civil Magistrate, not only the <hi>Franciscans,</hi> but the other
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:199119:80"/>Monks and all the wicked rabble of lasci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Priests were deservedly expell'd the City.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Franciscan</hi> lodging in a Gentleman's House of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigort,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Queen of</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varr<hi>'s Relation</hi>
                  </note> who was his Confessor, and very intimate with him, being privy to all his Secrets, by that Religious Cheat of auricular Confession, whereby he came to understand the Gentleman had a design to bed his Wife that Night, who had layn in but three weeks before; which the Confessor perswaded him to, only for his own wanton ends: for when Night approach'd, the Friar anticipated him, went to Bed to his Wife, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed her, who departed immediately after he had satisfied his Lust, as mute as a Fish, not so much as opening his lips, and went out of the Door, which the Porter took notice of; Presently after in comes her Husband at the time appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who thinking it was he that accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied her before, could not forbear discovering it; whereupon he suspected the Friar had play'd him that slippery
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:199119:80"/>trick, and finding him out of his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and the Porter confirming his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, he was satsfied 'twas he, went back to his Wife and acquainted her with the circumstances of the Story: and so left her, to pursue the <hi>Franciscan;</hi> but his Wife being alone, and extreamly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex'd, to rid her self of that trouble that was upon Spirit, hanged her self; but whilst she was strugling with the pangs of Death, killed a little Infant that was by her with a Blow of her Foot, which cried out so vehemently before Death, that a Woman who lay in the Chamber was awakened with the noise: and seeing these miserable Spectacles, went and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted her Mistrisse's Brother therewith, who asked her what Villain committed that butcherly Fact? she not being able to satisfie him with the Author of it, only said, she knew of no body that was there but her Master. He seeks for him, but finds him not, which did very much confirm him in the opinion, that he was guilty of the Murther. He follows him, over takes him, assaults him with a whole
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:199119:81"/>Volley of villanous Names, draws upon him so suddenly, that his Brother in Law had no time to ask him his Reason; so they fought desperately, and so long, that at last being tir'd out, they desisted by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, and then making inquiry into the cause of this furious and unexpected Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contre, he understood the <hi>Franciscan</hi> occasioned all this Mischief; his Brother that pursued him, crav'd his Pardon for fighting and wounding him, and mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him on his Horse, conducted him to his own Apartment, where he died the next Morning, freely forgiving his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Law, and acknowledging to his Relations, that he was the sole cause of his own Death; but his Brother, to satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Law, sued out his Pardon, which was granted him by King <hi>Francis</hi> the First. See the pregnant mischiefs, and complicated Crimes that did accompany the <hi>Furtiva Gaudia,</hi> the stollen sweets, or adulterous action of a Religious <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciscan.</hi> If this be their Religion and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, what must their Irreligion and Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be, and what dangerous effects must attend it?</p>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:199119:81"/>
               <p> It is storied of a Priest, that a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick coming to holy <hi>Shrift,</hi> shook his head at the thought of his Crimes which he was to Confess, but the Priest find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him somewhat disturbed, perswaded him to a free Declaration of his Sins in order to his Absolution; at last he told him, with much adoe, that he had deflowr'd a Virgin. Pish, said the Priest, If that be all; <hi>Innocentum docuisti,</hi> Thou hast in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed an innocent Person. Oh! but Sir, said he, I have committed a greater Crime. What's that? Why, I have bedded my Neighbour's Wife. Well then, said the Priest, <hi>Proximam adjuvasti;</hi> Thou hast helped thy Neighbour. Alas, Sir, said he, I have done worse than all this; I have had carnal knowledge of a Nun. At which the Confessor's zeal was so great, that he could not forbear cursing instead of absolving him, <hi>Abi apud inferos furci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, hoc est pro nobis.</hi> Go and be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, you Hang-dog, how durst you take the Trade out of our hands, that's our proper work, and no Lay-man's business.</p>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:199119:82"/>
               <p> That unnatural sin, which was burnt by fire and brimstone from Heaven, the ashes whereof were drowned in the dead Sea: hath made a shift to revive among <hi>Romanists,</hi> and cries as loud for Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance as ever; and of all Places <hi>Italy</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds most with frequent Examples of Incest and Sodomy. It is a common Proverb there among them;
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Siena di quatro cose se vanta,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Di Torre &amp; di Campane,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Di Bardasse &amp; di Putane.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>For these four things <hi>Siena</hi> far excells</l>
                        <l>All Places; Towers, Whores, Sodomy and Bells.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Venice,</hi> saith Mr <hi>Howel,</hi> all Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous things are done by Proxy; while the Husband is abroad in the Gallies, there be others that shoot the Gulph at home.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Rome,</hi> that Holy City, Pictures are Printed to provoke Lust, and to teach men obscenity by ocular demonstration;
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:199119:82"/>a thing which the very Heathens detest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Philaenis</hi> and <hi>Elephantis;</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertius</hi> the elegiack Poet inveighs against such filthy Draughts.
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Non istis olim variabant Tecta figuris,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Cum paries nullo crimine pictus erat.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Such Pictures n'ere adorn'd in former times</l>
                        <l>Houses, when Walls were painted with no crimes.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pietro Aloisio,</hi> Son to Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the third, was a Prince of Sodomy, he dealt with a great number of all Persons, of what Sex or degree soever, and at last courted a young man, <hi>Casmus Cherius,</hi> then Bishop of <hi>Fano;</hi> and because he found he was not to be brought to his ends, but by violence, he caused his Servant to hold him, whilst he used him as his Ingle.</p>
               <p>This sort of bestiality, Sodomy and Buggery, is frequent among the <hi>Italians,</hi> both Clergy and Laiety; for 'tis well known to any smattering Sciolist in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:199119:83"/>what beastly work the <hi>Italian</hi> Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers made with the Goats, when they beleaguer'd <hi>Lions,</hi> during the Civil Wars; now which were the greatest Brutes of the two, I leave it to all sober Men to judge. And this puts me in mind of a facetious, but filthy story, of a hot <hi>Neopolitan,</hi> in whose Country Absolutions are as cheap as Whores. There was a <hi>Calabrian</hi> who had buggered a Goat, he confest the fact to his ghostly Father, and bought an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution for it: a Friend of his hearing of it, said to him, Prethee what might it cost thee, for it was a heinous Crime? he answered, but four Pistolets, upon my word: and added, that for the other odd one I think verily I might have had a Dispensation to marry the Brute. This verifies the old saying;
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dulcis odor lucri ex re qualebet</hi>—</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The scent of Gain is sweet</l>
                        <l>From Sins tho ne'er so great.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>It is recorded in <hi>Pontanus,</hi> that <hi>Sigis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund Malatesta,</hi> Lord of <hi>Romagniola,</hi> got a Child by his own Daughter, nay,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:199119:83"/>that he designed to make a Pathick of his own Son <hi>Robert;</hi> but that he, in detesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Fathers wickedness, drew his Sword in his own defence, and so escaped the fury of his unnatural Lust: But this is barbarous, and beyond a Parallel, which he acted on a virtuous <hi>German</hi> Lady, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling to <hi>Rome</hi> through his Territories who seeing that his Courtship and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resses could no ways move her to conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend to his lustful desires, he first cut her throat, and then like a barbarous Lecher, made use of her dead body. The same <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus</hi> alledgeth, That there is to be found among Beasts themselves a certain natural honesty, to reprove and convince men of such gross crimes: speaking of a Bitch that would not suffer her own Whelp to lime her, but would fly at those that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to procure it; and of a Mare that would not let her own Colt cover her; but having at last leapt her, disguised in another colour'd Skin, and other tricks and devices used to that purpose; when she perceiv'd the Cheat, forsook her Mate, and died for grief soon after. The
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:199119:84"/>very Brutes may inform men of their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiality, and shame them out of such im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moral and criminal Principles and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctises.</p>
               <p>As for the Gluttony and Drunkenness of the Clergy, among many Instances take these few; It is grown Proverbial, Bishops fare, Prelates fare, Theological Wine, for the best, and Chapter bread for the finest. He fares like a Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, he swears like an Abbot, as fat as a Friar, as frolick as a Friar, and the like; and the truest of all, as fat as a Hog; For as one says wittily, Friars in <hi>puris na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalibus</hi> differ very little from Swine. nay, their good St. <hi>Anthony</hi> was but a Swine-heard <hi>ab initio,</hi> and their reverend Patron. And they are known to be such belly Gods, that 'tis a Proverbial saying, A Carmelite in the Kitchen.</p>
               <p>The boon Companions among the Clergy are so prodigiously prophane, that they must wrest the Scripture for Expressions to countenance their Intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance. They will jest with the two edged sword of God's Word. Nothing
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:199119:84"/>will please them but to wash their hands in the Font,
<note place="margin">Fuller<hi>'s Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly State.</hi>
                  </note> and so drink healths in the Church Chalice, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Glass that they take off must be hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd by this Prayer, <hi>Cor mundum crea in me Deus, &amp; Spiritum rectum innova in visceribus meis;</hi> and when they would signifie that the Wine is generous and good, <hi>Hic est tenete eum;</hi> and when 'tis all out, the Monks express themselves in this Allegory, <hi>Data nobis de oleo vestro, quia Lampades nostrae extinguuntur.</hi> The Abbot of <hi>Chartees</hi> being asked how he came to bear drink so well, and quaff so deeply? answered out of the Psalmist, <hi>Patris no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stri annunciaverunt nobis;</hi> And good Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows use to Droll with these words, <hi>Si quis Episcopatum desiderat bonum, opus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderat.</hi> Nay, they spare not their own Mass, for when a Malefactor is executed, they say, <hi>sursum corda;</hi> when a Man takes the Cup to drink, <hi>quia pius est.</hi> And some proceed farther, who are so bold as to belch forth these or the like sayings, Let God keep Heaven to himself, and let us alone to injoy our sensual pleasures
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:199119:85"/>upon Earth, like the <hi>French</hi> Clergy-man that would not part with his Benefice in <hi>Paris</hi> for his share in <hi>Paradice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Civil Wars of <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manists,</hi> to vex and disturb the poor Protestants, who began their Prayers with <hi>Nostre aide soit au nom de Dieu.</hi> Our help standeth in the name of the Lord, who made Heaven and Earth; being an Expression out of the Psalmist; they, I say, would begin their Game at Dice with the same Invocation, as if a Jest were not worth a Pin, if not seasoned with the Salt of the Sanctuary. Nay, there is not a Priest among them, but can give you three pregnat Arguments for their drinking the best unsophistica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Wine.</p>
               <p>First, because it prevents and disperseth those Crudities of the Stomach, which might otherwise by a Rebellious Insur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection fly up into the head, and so make them snivel and drivel when they areat their solemn and Religious Services.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Because Devotion in the opinion of these Religious Galenists, is
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:199119:85"/>more operative and fervent in a hot, then a cold Stomach.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, because they are to chant and sing Mass: Now 'tis the opinion of all Musicians, that a Man cannot sing worth a Button, till he has cleared his throat with a plentiful dose of good Liquor. But it may be the Bigot-Protestant will throw this rub in their way, that they are in danger of being Drunk; why, alas poor <hi>Ignaro!</hi> what if they be intoxicated, that signifies nothing, because they do it with a good Intention, for if it be allowable, and no ways hurtful to say, <hi>Hoc est Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum meum</hi> instead of <hi>Corpus meum,</hi> so it be done <hi>cum intentione consecrandi,</hi> or to cast a Child into a Well, though it be drowned, <hi>cum intentione Baptizandi,</hi> as some Glosses maintain; what then if a Priest take off his cups so freely, as to be fuddled, 'tis not amiss, so long as it is done <hi>cum intentione missificandi;</hi> and he is not obliged, maugre all the Laws of good-Fellowship, to Pay his Groat the next Morning, or to confess and Pay but his
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:199119:86"/>two-Pence: for the Priests are exempted from such pitiful Lay-penalties.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Cruelties, Murthers and Massacres committed by the Priests, Friars, and Laity of the Catholick Religion.</head>
               <p>THere was a <hi>French</hi> Priest at <hi>Orle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> who maintained a Whore, but grew jealous of her for false play with others, which the Religious man look'd upon as so heinous an affront to a person of his Coat and Order, that nothing could sufficiently expiate the Offence but death. The Priest invites her to the Tavern with accustomed kindness and familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, where being entred, he takes her aside, as if he intended to play the wanton with her, throws her upon a Bed, and cuts her throat with a Razor, which he carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his sleeve to that purpose, for which double crime he was only condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Imprisonment during life; a rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Punishment for those two priestly Vertues of Whoredom and Murder.</p>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:199119:86"/>
               <p> A <hi>Jacobine</hi> Friar of the holy House of <hi>Spain, John de Roan</hi> by name, was a cruel Persecutor of the poor unarm'd and unresisting Christians in <hi>Merindol</hi> and <hi>Cabriere;</hi> nay, his cruelty extended so far, that he put his wicked phancy upon the rack for new torments to torture these poor Protestants, and among the rest, this was none of the least; he used to fill Boots with boyling Oyle or Greace, and to force them on the legs of those that were to undergoe his Examination, to the end, that the violence and insuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable extremity of the pain might so di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stract them, that they should not be able to give any other than disjoynted and impertinent answers to all Questions pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bernard, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Jacobine</hi> Friar, being one of the Faction of the <hi>Guelphs,</hi> poyson<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Henry</hi> the 7th, with the flesh of our Saviour in the holy Eucharist, of which we have given you a hint in another place before.</p>
               <p>Nor are the <hi>Romish</hi> Laity altogether guiltless of these kind of Cruelties, tho
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:199119:87"/>the two neat Examples, relish more of witty severity than of palpable Cruelty.</p>
               <p>The Curate of <hi>Onzain,</hi> near <hi>Amboise</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> he had an extraordinary kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness for his much beloved Hostess; but she, like a crafty Quean, to prevent the jealousie of her Husband, set him upon an Imposture which put a Period to his Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerial sport for ever, namely, to pretend that he had a real design to be gelded, and that she would provide an able Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist, and very expert at the Trade of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration to do it, <hi>Monsieur Pierre des Serpens.</hi> The Priest, who thought no pretence grievous, that might conduce to his lascivious ends; desires to speak with his kindred, who accordingly came to know his Pleasure; they no sooner appeared, but he acquainted them with his firm and settled resolution of making himself an Eunuch, in order to the happy State of a future Being, and to prevent all illicite Insurrections hereafter; and thereupon in the presence of them all, made and published his solemn last Will and Testament; and withal, the better to confirm the matter, did freely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:199119:87"/>Mr. <hi>Peter,</hi> if he should dye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his hands, tho he had privately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted with him before to give him five <hi>French</hi> Crowns as a Reward, that he should only make a shew of doing that which was thought he really intended; so the Patient was fast bound, and handled as one that was to be cut indeed. But the Host receiving Intelligence of the slippery Trick, he design'd to Put upon him, paid him in his own Coin, and gave him as good as he brought, for he covenanted with him for twice as much, to do the business ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, and he would bear him harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less; so my nimble Shaver, for lucre of the Reward went dextrously to work and eastrated him indeed, telling him withal, when he had effected it to purpose, that he did not use to make a Fool of himself, nor a mock of his Occupation. Thus the poor Priest, contrary to his expectation, was dismembred by this unlucky Fellow, and I think it was a sufficient Caution to avoid jesting with edged Tools for the future.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Savoyard, Monsieur d' Avanchi,</hi> one that had no great kindness for Priests and Nuns, and therefore took great delight
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:199119:88"/>in disobliging of them, knowing the Wickedness of their Inclinations, and the Vitiousness of their Actions, made two <hi>Franciscans</hi> first very merry, and at last very mad; for having invited them to his Castle and treated them very nobly, to complete their good Entertainment, profer'd them the use of his Miss, which, like a couple of dissembling Varlets, they at first refus'd very nicely; but he desir'd them to embrace his kind proffer, and assur'd them of their Welcome, and told them, that this was but a modest Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulse, for he knew they were Flesh and Blood as well as other men, and stood in need of such Refrigerations. In con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion, he lock'd them up in a Chamber together; and they were not such Fools as to lose so fair an Opportunity, but to work they went; and when he upon his Return found they had not been idle, O wicked Hypocrites, said he, Is this the way to overcome Temptations? I'll teach you better things. Immediately he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed them to be strip'd stark naked, and there he and his Man belabour'd them as
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:199119:88"/>long as they could stand over them; and after they were severely lash'd, sent them away with never a Rag to cover their shame, to teach them never to encounter Temptations at all, or to fight more cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiously against them. Thus did this <hi>Ajax Flagellifer</hi> lash them severely, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the whipping of themselves, which they sometimes do, but I believe more favourably.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pontanus. Nicholas Fortibrachius,</hi> an <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> Captain, went always attended with a Mute laden with Halters; and when the Fit came on him, he would make a Sign to the dumb Man, who upon this Signal soon dispatched the next Person that came in his way upon the next Tree that was at hand.</p>
               <p>A Virtuous Lady, whose Husband was imprisoned by the <hi>Provost la Vouste,</hi> made her Addresses to him on behalf of her Husband, the Criminal: and after she had earnestly supplicated him, he told her in plain terms, there could be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing done under the rate of a Nights Lodging with her, and then he would
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:199119:89"/>grant her Request. The distressed Lady being in this great Strait and anxious Condition, was at a very strange loss: but after a serious Debate with her self, resolved to purchase her Husbands Life with the loss of her Honour; but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, first acquainted him with her Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to which he soon condescended; and so his Lordship had his Desire: but like a sordid Wretch, after he had defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Gentlewoman, the very next Morning hanged up her Husband, and then said, I promised you you should have your Husband, and I scorn to be worse than my Word; here take him dead.</p>
               <p>In the Reign of <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, there was a famous Covent of <hi>Franciscans</hi> in <hi>Flanders,</hi> within his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, near which there dwelt a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, who was a great Favourer of that Order, among whom there was a lusty proper Brother of the Society, who was the Gentleman's Confessor, and gave him full Power over his whole Family; Now having this Liberty, he came in and out when he pleas'd, insomuch that at
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:199119:89"/>last he was inflam'd with his Wife's Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and one day above all the rest, he visited her, and inquir'd where her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was: she told him he was gone abroad to survey some Lands that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd to him, and would be absent two or three days. The <hi>Franciscan</hi> walks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout very disconsolately; which the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman perceiving, sent her Maid to him to know if he wanted any thing; she came to him in the Court and asked him if he had occasion for any thing that the House could afford? and he said, yes: and leading her into a bye Corner, took a Dagger out of his Sleeve and thrust it into her Throat. In the <hi>interim,</hi> one of the Gentleman's Tenants came into the Court to bring his Landlord's Rent; who spying the <hi>Franciscan,</hi> he embraced him very courteously: but the wicked Fryar, to requite his Kindness, stab'd him, and then lock'd up the Castle Gate. The Gentlewoman wondring that her Maid stay'd so long, sent another to know the reason of it, and he serv'd her as he did the former. Then he went to
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:199119:90"/>the Gentlewoman, there being none but they two in the House, and told her plainly, he had been in love with her a long time, and was resolved now to fulfill his desire, intreating her to come down, which she did, and there saw her Maids and Tenant dead; telling her that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have his pleasure on her, more than once, and therefore would not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vish her; but pulled off his Habit, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which he had a shorter, which he profered her, and said, if she would not accept of it, he would deal by her as he had done by the rest: She protracted the time as long as she could, in hopes of some assistance; and when she had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dress'd her head, her hair being loose a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her Ears, he cut it off, and made her strip to her Smock, and so cloathed her with his short Habit, and put on his long Robe again, so they both departed; but it fortuned, that her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band had dispatch'd his business, and was upon his return the same way that they went: The Friar spying him, said to her, look yonder is your Husband, go before,
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:199119:90"/>and if you give him the least sign I will cut your throat; the Gentleman ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, asked the Friar whence he came, he said from his own House, where I left my Mistriss your Wife in health, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting you, and so he past on, but his Man called to her, thinking it had been Friar <hi>John,</hi> the <hi>Franciscan</hi>'s old Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion; But she durst not give him a word, only a wink with a weeping Eye; the Fellow rides after his Master, and told him that Novice did resemble his Mistriss: Go, said he, thou talkest like a Fool; but the Servant was so dissatisfied, that he went back, his Master staying to know the issue; he calls out aloud, Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar <hi>John;</hi> whereat the <hi>Franciscan</hi> fearing a Discovery, turned back upon him, and with a long quarter-staff knock'd him off his Horse, and when he was down, fell upon him and cut his throat, the Master seeing his Man fall, made up to them, which the Friar perceiving, beat him down, and fell upon him, but the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman being very strong, grasped him in his Armes that he could do him no
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:199119:91"/>hurt, and the Dagger in the Scuffle fell out of his hand, which his Wife took up, and gave her Husband, she holding him down by the Cowle, whilst her Husband stabbed him in several places, insomuch that he confessed the Villany, and begg'd his Pardon; The Gentleman being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to kill him, sent his Wife home for some of his Servants, who came thither immediately, so they took up the <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciscan,</hi> carried him to the Gentleman's, and from thence to the Emperours Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in <hi>Flanders,</hi> to whom he confessed the whole matter, and upon his Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it was found, that abundance of beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Gentlewomen had been so served. In short, the Women so detained were all fetch'd out of the Monastery, and the Friars and their Covent were burned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:199119:91"/>
               <head>Of the Necromancy, Sorcery, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurations of Priests and Friars.</head>
               <p>FRiar <hi>Lewis,</hi> about 100 years ago, made an absolute Paction with the Devil, who appeared to him at <hi>Marseilles</hi> in the shape of a Goat, and promised him (I wonder the Friar had no more Wit than to believe him, since he was a Lyar from the beginning) the uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted enjoyment of any Woman what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, tho never so great a Beauty; or of any other Pleasures for the term of 41 years complete, but the Devil was too cunning an Arithmetician for him, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the unite before the tens, which amounted but to 14 years, (and this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Contract is to be seen to this day, with the Devil's Claw to it,) when the time was expir'd, the Friar was detected of Witchcraft and burnt; all the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren he had christned during that dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Apprentiship of twice seven years, being rebaptized; and the Women he had abused were confined to a Nunnery by themselves.</p>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:199119:92"/>
               <p> There was a cetain Priest of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who was Curate of the Village <hi>Feling,</hi> near <hi>Bonne,</hi> to whom his Parishioners resorted in great flocks, to beg of him that he would allay a violent Tempest that then raged among them; for he had often made his brags he could do it, and that they need not fear either Thunder, Lightning, or any Tempest, so long as he continued among them. Well, to work my Conjurer goes, and mumbles over a great many Conjurations, which he had by roat, being only a Medley of horrible, terrible, hard words, as dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the People as the Tempest it self, (he being sheltered all this while under a thick well-spread Tree, and held by four or five for fear of being blown away) but finding himself at a loss in his Art, to mend the matter, pulled out his bread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en God, and saluted it in this irreverend manner, according to the harsh Dialect of his Country; <hi>Cour di, se te ne ple for que le Diablou, &amp;c.</hi> By God's heart, if thou be not stronger than the Devil, I'll throw thee into the dirt. And this
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:199119:92"/>did the business effectually. Avant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all <hi>Agrippa's,</hi> and <hi>Merlins;</hi> let not <hi>Spanheim</hi> boast any more of her grand Wizard-Abbot, since <hi>Savoy</hi> hath clearly out-done her with a little Conjuring Curate.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Savoy Anno</hi> 1358, several Priests were burnt for Incantations, and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, and one of them a notorious Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman in the Black-Art, was executed at <hi>Rolle,</hi> a Town four miles distant from <hi>Lausana,</hi> who had been a Wizard or Sorcerer, as appeared by his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, for four and twenty Years, and yet all this time sung Mass, and perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the office of a Priest, as religiously as the best Mass-monger of them all; and that he might not suffer uncomfortably, and dye alone, his Whore was burnt with him for company; and 'twas but just, that she who had been a long time Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partner with him in Pleasure, should at last be partaker with him in Pain; and it seems she imployed her Talent so well, that she grew Mistriss of the Trade too, and was so expert in it, that she was
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:199119:93"/>found Guilty, and condemned as a Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceress. Thus these two Hellish, but lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Mates to the very last embraced one another in the hot Flames, a just reward or guerdon of their fiery Lust, and Hellish practices of this nature for many years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, formerly by them put in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for which they were both in the end (as you have heard) executed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the gross Ignorance of the Priests and Friars, their falve Impositions upon the Laity.</head>
               <p>THere is a known story of <hi>Monsieur Prat,</hi> the Chancellor of <hi>Paris,</hi> a <hi>Reverendissimo,</hi> and grave Clergy-man in the time of <hi>Francis</hi> the First, who had a Present sent him by <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, King of <hi>England,</hi> with a Letter wherein there was this Expression, <hi>Mitto tibi</hi> 12 <hi>Molossos,</hi> I send you twelve Mastives; but the profoundly learned Chancellor, mistook the meaning for a dozen of Mules, and being over confident of this Exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he went to the King, accompanied
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:199119:93"/>with an eminent Noble-man at Court, to intreat his Master to bestow on him that Present, which the King of <hi>England</hi> had sent him; but King <hi>Francis</hi> having heard nothing of it, commanded them to produce the Letter, that he might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>use it; and the rather, because that Mules in <hi>England</hi> are as rarely seen as Coaches in <hi>Venice:</hi> But when his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty found out the gross mistake, the Chancellor was the sole object of their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessive Laughter; who, like a State-Tink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to mend the matter, did excuse him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self with this kind of evasion, That he misunderstood <hi>Molossos</hi> for <hi>Muletos,</hi> like an Ass as he was, which latter mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpretation rendred his Lordship far more Ridiculous than the former.</p>
               <p>We read of an aged Priest,
<note place="margin">R. Pacaeus de fructu Doctrinae.</note> who lived in the Reign of our <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, who was so sordidly ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and stupid, that he always read in his <hi>Portesse Mumpsimus Domine,</hi> for <hi>Sumpsimus Domine,</hi> and being told of his error by a Friend that heard it, who was a Wel-wisher of him, and would needs
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:199119:94"/>have made him change his note, yet the Cuckow would not, for this very reason, because he had used <hi>Mumpsimus</hi> these 30 Years, (the more Block-head He) and therefore he would not leave his old <hi>Mumpsimus,</hi> for their new fangled <hi>Sumpsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus;</hi> No not he, it was fitter for a young Novice of his Order, to follow the new Modes of refined modern Speech, and not for a Man of his Years and Gravity. Nay, the Priests in general, when they had very shrewdly crack'd <hi>Priscian</hi>'s Crown, and were taken in the fact, would only use that common Defence out of St. <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory,</hi> tho never intended for their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, <hi>Non debent verba coelestis Oraculi sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>esse verbis Donati;</hi> The words of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Writ, ought not to be subject to the Rules of the <hi>Grammarian Donatus.</hi> But this was very hard usage from them to break the poor old-Man's head, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beg his Pardon, nor give him a Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</p>
               <p>Nay farther, these learned Men, whose Duty it is to instruct the Ignorant, and undeceive the seduced, are so far from
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:199119:94"/>informing their Sheep, that they, the very Pastors, want Instruction themselves, for if in their Lectures, which are but few, and seldom performed, they chance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily to stumble at a <hi>Greek</hi> Phrase, they tumble over it with a <hi>non legitur, Graecum est;</hi> or else pass it over with a <hi>Transeat, Graecum est.</hi> Away with it, 'tis <hi>Greek.</hi> We have nothing to do with it, it does not at all belong to us. And to shew the acuteness of their Wit in their Derivations, and Skill in the <hi>Etimologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Art, they derive <hi>Presbyter,</hi> from <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bens iter,</hi> as the Conductor or Pilot of Souls; but their Allusion is far more true, when they say,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>This</hi> Etimologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>Art is pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised by</hi> Hugo Carrensis, <hi>and several of their Praedicants.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>quasi prae aliis bibens ter,</hi> and 'tis very favourable too, for they ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally are so rude as to drink all, and leave none for the Company; Nay, the Devil himself cannot escape their biting Wit, for they derive <hi>Diabolus</hi> from <hi>dia, duo, &amp; bolus, morcellus, quast faciens duo bolos de corpore et anima,</hi> as making two morcels or choice bits of a Man, one of his Soul, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:199119:95"/>of his Body; and herein they give the Devil his due, and make him a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Abaddon or Apollion.</p>
               <p>A certain Sir <hi>John,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Stevens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology.</note> who deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be recorded as much as canonized for his Sanctity, when he came to the story of the Woman in the Gospel who lost a Groat, and swept her House in hopes to find it; He himself soon lost it in the rubbish; for he read, <hi>Evertit do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum,</hi> instead of, <hi>everrit domum;</hi> and whereas in the <hi>Acts</hi> it is said, <hi>demisimus per sportam,</hi> they write it, <hi>per portam;</hi> and in honour of this Translation, this <hi>Quatrain</hi> was made by a <hi>French</hi> Poet;
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Par ici passa devant hier</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ʋn tresnotable Charpentier,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Qui besogna de telle sorte,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Que d'un Panier fit une porte.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Here passed by the other day</l>
                        <l>A notable Carpenter this way,</l>
                        <l>He was no bungler at his Trade,</l>
                        <l>Who of a Basket a Door made.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:199119:95"/>
               <p> A <hi>French</hi> Curate, being angry with his Parishioners, because the Pavement of the Church was so much out of Repair, to prove it a Duty incumbent upon them to see that rectified, pleaded the 17th of <hi>Jerem.</hi> in his own Justification, and for their Confutation; out of these words, <hi>Paveant illi &amp; non paveam ego;</hi> let them pave the Church if they will, I have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with it, 'tis their business and not mine, so let them look after it, for my part I'll be no ways concerned, even as they Brew, so let them Bake, and there's an end of the Story.</p>
               <p>An ignorant Priest in <hi>Paris,</hi> finding in his <hi>Almanack, Sol</hi> in <hi>Cancer,</hi> in red Letters, mistook it for some Saint, and took a great deal of pains to find out a Mass suitable to that Holy day; turning his Mass book over and over, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to no purpose, was in so mad a Mood, that he closed his <hi>Mattins</hi> with this strange and barbarous Conclusion, <hi>Sol</hi> in <hi>Cancro, Sol</hi> in <hi>Cancrus, nec est Virgo, nec martyrus, venite adoremus.</hi> Now I'll be bold to say, there's never a
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:199119:96"/>Satchel-boy that has had Protestant E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, but would scorn to throw out such false and incongruous Latin.</p>
               <p>We will conclude this witty discourse with a facetious, though old rhythming Epitaph, made upon a Father in times of Yore;
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et mourut quatre cents &amp; neuf,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tout plein de vertu comme un oeuf.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>He died ith' year four hund'red and nine complete,</l>
                     <l>As full of Grace as an Egg's full of Meat.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Abbess, Nuns, and Religious Women.</head>
               <p>NUN is a word derived from the <hi>Egyptian Nonna,</hi> of the same signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and truly their Confinement would be no less than an <hi>Egyptian</hi> Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, but that their <hi>Pharaoh</hi> is somewhat indulgent to that Sex, and both their Task<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masters and Task very easie and delightful. They have several other denominations, as
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:199119:96"/>Religiosas, Devota's, Votresses, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all originally derived from fine words, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Devotion, Vows of Virginity, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stity, and the like; but whether these are broken or kept, judge you by the sequel.</p>
               <p>They have adopted one name to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, that discovers their Life and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation against their wills, and that is, <hi>Recluses,</hi> which in its native and genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine Signification, speaks no more than to be set open, or left at their own liberty and disposal; tho the Learned Patrons of that barbarous Age, wherein it was first started, mistook the meaning for those that are closely shut up, and inclosed within the round of a Religious Cloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joan</hi> Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> was the first Authress of those Epicoene Monasteries, as one fitly call's them, wherein Men and Women did cohabit and live together (very religiously and chastly no doubt of it) under one Roof; And here, forty to one else, the dull Hugonot will ask, why Nuns should be lodged near the Friars? Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly soul, God-wot, there's a question with
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:199119:97"/>all my heart; when every ingenious <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manist</hi> will soon choak him with this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, The reason is this, because the Barn ought to be near the Threshers.</p>
               <p>Now if you scruple the truth of this Saying; <hi>Boccace</hi> will furnish you with a Precedent to confirm it, and one that is very pertinent, and to the purpose. For he tells you of an Abbess in <hi>Lombardie,</hi> that rose in great haste from a jolly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norite, who upon pretence of shriving her, took an occasion to lye with her, and bedded her all that night, saw one of her Nuns at the same sport with her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramour; but the Reverend Governess ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king more haste then good speed, instead of her Veil clapt on the Friars Breeches, the points of them hanging down on each side, as ill luck would have it, and came to her chamber big with reproof, resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to nettle her for her Lasciviousness, (see how old Vice corrects youthful Sin) when she her self was piping hot with the same wanton Conflict; but the poor Nun, being about to receive her <hi>Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite,</hi> by chance spied her Head geer, that
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:199119:97"/>priestly ornament, and said, Madam, I beseech you first tye your Coife, before you proceed any farther, and then I am content to receive patiently your sharpest Reprehension; but the Abbesse finding her gross mistake, soon chang'd her mind, and went sneaking away, without bidding her farewell, which shew'd very little breeding; but had her education been never so good, this unlucky Accident was enough to spoil it, that's the very truth of it. Surely my Paper would be of a more ruddy complexion than natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally it is, for bearing the Contents of this Story, but that I find the <hi>Italian</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb is like the Pope, infallible; which says, that Paper cannot blush. This Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry puts me in mind of <hi>Scoggin's</hi> wonder, who taking a Friar in bed with a Whore, cried out, a Miracle! a Miracle! Here is to be seen A Friar with four Legs.
<note place="margin">The Anatomy of the English Nunnery at <hi>Lisbon,</hi> writ by a young Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of that Covent.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Author of the Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of the English Nunnery at <hi>Lisbon</hi> who was once a Brother of that Society, tells us, as a Witness of their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stity,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:199119:98"/>that he could go directly to a Place in the Wall of their Covent, where he might pull out the bones of Legs and Arms of the poor innocent Bastards, that have been both got and murther'd by that Common Society.</p>
               <q>— <hi>Saxa ipsa trabesque Loquntur.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>This verifies the old Proverb; There's cunning in dawbing. Nay, 'tis certain, that these Tricks have been us'd some Centuries of Years, or else Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> could never have found so many Bones of drowned Infants as he did: and that they were very numerous is no wonder, being found in so spatious a Place; for his Pond must needs be very large indeed, whose See is universal. <hi>Inter Coenandum hilares,</hi> was the old rule; and you'l find it observ'd among the Nuns of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> where this Story was related in their Covent, by one of that Society, to foster her ghosty Father, as pleasant Table-talk, by one that had been formerly a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-maid
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:199119:98"/>forsooth, in the very house where the Comedy was really acted.</p>
               <p>Father <hi>Strange,</hi> a young Jesuit, who had been brought up in <hi>England,</hi> fell very sick, the Air it seems of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Valedolid</hi> in <hi>Spain</hi> being unhealthful, and disagreeing with his Constitution; which made him beg leave of the Rector to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into <hi>England,</hi> and 'twas obtain'd, in Order to the recovery of his health, and partly also for the converting, or rather perverting of Hereticks: where he no sooner arriv'd, but he took up this Nun's Ladies Chamber for his Quarters, and in a small time threw off his Distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and grew very lusty; insomuch that he had a great mind to be dabbling with that young Gentlewoman, his Sister <hi>Anne's</hi> Mistris; for that was her name, that made this relation. Mrs. <hi>Anne</hi> it seems was then sitting at her Needle-Work, with her back to her Lady, and the brisk recover'd Jesuit, who were by the fire side; and she looking by chance in a great looking Glass that hung before her, spied the late sick Jesuit at work, and
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:199119:99"/>withall saw what pains he took to shrieve her Mistriss; but he found before he had ended his shrift, he was discover'd, and suspecting the truth, that she had seen all, he took her aside, and told her, that he was a man, and Flesh and Blood as well as others, was subject to such failings, tho he had vowed Chastity; using all the Perswasions imaginable to win her to Secresy; and the better to effect it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised her, that if she at any time stood in need of a Confessor to absolve her for any of her sweet Sins (as he call'd them) he would perform that Office, and her Penance should not be grievous or burthensome. This was undoubtedly enough to keep a she Saint from tatling. Do but ghess by this at the sober Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation of a profess'd Nun; of the Jesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it's Chastity in the Action, her modesty in the Relation, who did not blush to tell this tale for her own and her Ghostly Fathers Recreation; who, like an old Fornicator, would report it with delight in his jovial humour, as he did to me (said
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:199119:99"/>the Author) and one Father <hi>Vivian,</hi> a Friar of the same House.</p>
               <p>Nay, 'tis very frequent among them, for the Father Confessor to go alone into the Nuns Cloister, or Side, and continue there a whole day together, and Dine at their Table with them, and be every o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day in their sight, tho it be express<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly against their Rules; and in the Cell, which is only for them at Confession, they have a Grate, which is usually taken down with a slight, through which the Holy Nuns pass to his Bed by night; a cleanly conveyance for such lustful Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons: nor indeed can it well be expected to be otherwise, since they have such Provocations to this Sin, as Pride, Ease, fulness of Bread, and abundance of all Things, and those the best that can be had for Mony; for many times those costly Viands which the Viceroy's Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyor will not meddle with, because they they are so dear, the Caterer of such Houses will buy, tho never so unreasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which Provisions are made for the ghostly Father's Table; and when they sit at
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:199119:100"/>their Meals, sing bawdy Songs, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scene Catches to please their Confessor, playing the most loose and wanton Tunes upon Instruments, such as would make a chaste ear glow, and a modest Person colour at the hearing. And this is the constant practise of these Religious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, whose Covent is made a meer Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel-House, daily practising such lascivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Actions as are scarce known or heard of in some common Stews.</p>
               <p>But my Pen being tired with writing such unheard of Villanies; take this for a Corollary to all the precedent Matter. If Blasphemy, Treason, and Simony, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly countenanced, but daily practised and applauded as works mertorious, by a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suasion call'd Religion be the way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; if Massacres, Murders, and Assassina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be pious and good Acts, and can help the Soul to everlasting Felicity; If King-killing, deposing of Emperours and Princes, be not only commendable, but works of Supererogation, and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the means to obtain Salvation; If Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Buggery, Incest, and all sorts of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanness,
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:199119:100"/>are not only allowable, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferable in some Cases to Chastity, and Matrimony; if these, or any of these Qualifications can bring us into the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of immortal Bliss and Happiness; Then he is to blame that will live an Austere, Sober, Religious, and Godly Life, and much to blame if he turns not a Proselyte, and imbrace the <hi>Roman</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which is of so great a Latitude, as to allow what Morality, nay, Paganism it self, abhors as Unnatural and Bestial; therefore much more should every Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, who pretends to Christianity, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test and abominate such a Religion, whose Tenets and Practises are so Hellish and Damnable.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:199119:101"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of Books Printed for, and sold by <hi>James Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> at the <hi>King's Armes</hi> without <hi>Temple-Barr.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>MAssinello;</hi> or a Satyr against the Association and the <hi>Guild Hall</hi> Riot, Quarto.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Eromena:</hi> or the Noble Stranger. A cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Novel. Octavo.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Tractatus adversus Reprobationis absolutae decretum, Nova Methodo &amp; succentissimo Compendio adornatus &amp; in duos Libros digestus. Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. An <hi>Idea</hi> of Happiness, in a Letter to a Friend, enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring wherein the greatest Happiness attainable by man in this Life does consist. Quarto.</p>
            <p n="5">5. A Murnival of Knaves, or Whiggism plainly display'd, and (if not grown shameless) Burlesqu'd out of Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. Quarto.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Accomplisht Lady, or Deserving Gentlewoman: Being a Vindication of Innocent and Harmless Females from the aspersions of Malicious Men; wherein are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained many Eminent Examples of the Constancy, Chasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Prudence, Policy, Valour, Learning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> wherein they have not only equall'd, but excell'd many of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Sex.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Patria Parricida:</hi> or the History of the horrid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracy of <hi>Catiline</hi> against the Commonwealth of <hi>Rome,</hi> in <hi>English.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Core Redivivus:</hi> In a Sermon Preached at <hi>Christ-Church</hi> Tabernacle in <hi>London,</hi> upon Sunday, <hi>September</hi> 9. being a Day of Publick Thanksgiving for the Deliverance of His Sacred Majesties Person and Government from the late Treasonable Rebellion and Fanatick Conspiracy.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:199119:101"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>